<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short and plain way to the faith and church composed many years since by Richard Hudleston ; and now published ... by Jo. Hudleston : to which is annexed His late Majesty King Charles the Second his papers found in his closet after his decease : as also a brief account of what occurred on his death-bed in regard to religion.</title>
            <author>Hudleston, Richard, 1583-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44862</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">8163876</idno>
  <idno type="VID">40980</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248508314</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24387</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">08163876</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44862)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40980)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1231:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short and plain way to the faith and church composed many years since by Richard Hudleston ; and now published ... by Jo. Hudleston : to which is annexed His late Majesty King Charles the Second his papers found in his closet after his decease : as also a brief account of what occurred on his death-bed in regard to religion.</title>
                  <author>Hudleston, Richard, 1583-1655.</author>
                  <author>Hudleston, John, 1608-1698.</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Re-printed for William Weston,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed by the author's nephew, John Hudleston.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Faith.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Bishops --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40980:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40980:1"/>
            <p>A SHORT AND PLAIN WAY TO THE FAITH AND CHURCH.</p>
            <p>COMPOSED Many Years since by that Eminent Divine Mr. RICHARD HUDLESTON of the English Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Order of St. <hi>Benedict.</hi> And now published for the common Good by his Nephew Mr. JO. HUDLESTON of the same Congregation.</p>
            <p>To which is Annexed his late Majesty King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second his Papers found in his Closet after his Decease.</p>
            <p>As also a Brief Account of what occurred on his Death-Bed in Regard to Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Permissu Superiorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>DƲBLIN,</hi> Re-printed for <hi>William Weston,</hi> Bookseller in <hi>High street,</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:40980:2"/>
            <p>Re-Imprimatur, </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>22 Aprilis 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Patr. Clogherens.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:40980:2"/>
            <head>TO THE QUEEN DOWAGER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is not only the Honor I have of being in your Majesties service ever since your first Accession to the Crown of these Realms, which gives Me the Boldness to lay this little Offering at your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Feet: But the Book it self brings along with it so many good qualities, which will Recommend it to your Majesties perusal, that I thought I could do no less. For it contains the most excellent sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and that which lies nearest your Royal Heart, the Doctrin of the Catholic Church: and this so clearly deduced, and evinced, that I dare say, it shines no where brighter except in your Majesties Life and Example. Ecclesiastical Writers only draw the Lines, while the Lives of good Christians lay on the Colors: And tho' <hi>all the Glory of the Kings Daughter be from within,</hi> yet all the Beauty which charms the Eye, and renders the Church as Lovely, as she is Holy, is <hi>from without,</hi> in the Piety of her Children, especially of Queens; so
<pb facs="tcp:40980:3"/> that this <hi>Theory</hi> added to your Majesties <hi>Practic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> mutually Illustrating each other, I am persuaded sufficient to convince the most obstinate of the <hi>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sonableness of our Service,</hi> on the one hand; and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the other, to force this Confession from the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Prejudic'd, that such an eminent, uninterrupte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> course of Devotion and every good work, canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be inspir'd or maintain'd, but by a Religion <hi>pure an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> undefiled,</hi> and guiltless of all those Blemishes whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Ignorant and Malicious cast upon it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, by presenting this Book to your Majesty, I do a Duty to Religion, and an Act of Justice to the learned Author, by setting his Doctrin in the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Light. But your Majesty has a Title to it which is incommunicable, and which you will esteem the fairest Flower in your Crown; it being read, and approv'd and highly commended by his late Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty of ever Blessed and Glorious Memory, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laid the Foundation of that Conversion of his to the Catholic Church, of which your Majesty is so irrefragable a Witness, and which your Majesty would look upon as the happiest moment of your own Life as well as of His, had it not been so near his Last. But if this Consideration affords your Majesty the greatest subject of Comfort, the view of this Book will furnish You with as great an on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Admiration; It calling to your Mind the secre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:40980:3"/> workings of Gods Providence, which forgets not to be Merciful, even when we lie under the scour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of his Displeasure. This Book fell into the Kings hands when almost all other were armed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him: It was his faithful Companion, when all the World had deserted him, but shewed that God had not. At that very time when the Power of Darkness prevailed, and began to overspread three Kingdoms, Almighty God by the means of this Book made Light to shine out of Darkness, and began thus early to recomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce his Temporal Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scurity in his retirement at <hi>Moseley</hi> in <hi>Staffordshire,</hi> by Sowing in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Heart the Seeds of an indeficient Light, which through all the Opposition of the three Enemies of Mankind, by the unwearied hand of Providence wrought themselves at last into a perfect Day. And as that Providence made me an unworthy Instrument in preserving the person of my Sovereign, (which I mention, not to Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate any thing to my self, for I did no more than the Principles of my Religion, and Allegiance obliged me to) so it appointed me the Keeper of this Excellent Treatise, to which God gave such an Admirable Increase. And the same Reasons which made me keep it ever since as a great Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, have at length prevailed with me to make it public, that others may enrich themselves by it.
<pb facs="tcp:40980:4"/> After which Resolution taken, I did not long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate to whom I should make the first Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it, it being your Majesties in Right of the King: And as such I lay it with my self at your Sacred Feet, being</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               <signed>Your Majesties most Faithful most Humble and most Obedient Subject and Chaplain. <hi>JOHN HUDLESTON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:40980:4"/>
            <head>The Publisher to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THO' this great in little Volume needs no other Recommendation than the bare Perusal, nor the Writer of it other Encomium than his bare Name to give credit to both; the Work it self ennobling the Author, and the Author the Work; yet to give each it's due weight, and let the Reader more clearly understand as well the Fruit by the Tree, as the Tree by the Fruit: Take here a short abstract first of the Authors Life, next of the Reasons or Motives of this present Publication. Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the first, please to know the Book was long since composed for the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinal Instruction of a private friend, by my Uncle Mr. <hi>Rich. Hudleston</hi> the Youngest Son of <hi>Andrew Hudleston</hi> of <hi>Farrington</hi> Hall in <hi>Lancashire.</hi> He was Born towards the end of the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> when he arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the Years of Maturity for Studies, he was sent to <hi>Rhemes</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> where he became an exquisit Proficient in Poetry and Rhetoric: from <hi>Rhemes</hi> he went to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he passed his Schools of Philosophy and Divinity with an improvement proportionable to his great Wit and Industry. These Studies compleated, That he might effectually advance as well in Piety as Learning, he entered into a Religious State, and was professed at famous <hi>Mont-Cassine,</hi> the first Monastery founded by the Holy Patriarc St. <hi>Benedict</hi> in <hi>Italy.</hi> In this Holy Place he spent divers Years in Solitude, Prayer, Reading the Scriptures, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, Fathers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In which Theory having attained an Eminent degree of Perfection, at length, throughly qualified for an Apostolick Missioner he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned into <hi>England.</hi> Here like another St. <hi>Augustin</hi> endued with an Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Spirit he exerted his Talents in Preaching, Teaching, Disputing, and Reducing his strayed Country-men to the Sheep-fold of Christ: And it pleased the Divine Goodness to bless his endeavors, and second his Words with extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary success. In all as well publick Debates, as private Conferences he still came off a Conqueror; insomuch that many chief Families as those of the <hi>Irelands, Watertons, Middletons, Traps</hi>'s, <hi>Thimbelbyes,</hi> &amp;c. in <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire.</hi> Those of the <hi>Prestons, Andertons, Downs</hi>'s, <hi>Straffords, Sherbourns, Ingelbyes.</hi> &amp;c. in <hi>Lancashire:</hi> With numberless others of all States and Conditions, owe next to God, their respective Reconciliations to this worthy <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictine.</hi> But I do not pretend here to frame a Panegyric, it may suffice in short to aver, That the Purity of his Life bore equal Measures with the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of his Doctrin; both unblemished: And that after Thirty Years of Faithful Labors in Christ's Vinyard, He rested in Peace, leaving behind him a Sweet Odor of Vertue to all Posterity. He Writ on several Occurences several Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises, of which one is this small but <hi>Fortunate</hi> Book we now Publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sh; <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:40980:5"/> I say, in that (God so Ordaining) it became an occasional Instrument towards the Conversion of our late Sovereign Lord King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, to the Faith and Unity of the Catholick Church.</p>
            <p>To explain my self in this matter; The malignity of the times, and the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asters ensuing thereupon for above these Forty Years, have been too pernicious to be soon forgot. There are none so Ignorant who have not heard of the Defeat of his late Majesties Army by the Rebels at <hi>Worcester,</hi> on the 3d of <hi>September, 1651.</hi> And of the then Preservation of His Sacred Life and Person by the Care and Fidelity of his Catholic Subjects, of whom I acknowledg my self the most unworthy. In this sad Conjuncture it was, That the desolate King after having been harassed to and fro, Night and Day in continual Fatigues and Perils, from <hi>Wednesday</hi> the Day of the Battle till <hi>Sunday</hi> following (the particulars of which are out of the Sphere of my present design to enlarge upon) at last found an Asylum and Refuge at Mr. <hi>Whitgrave</hi>'s House at <hi>Moseley,</hi> whither Divine Providence, not long before, brought me, and where I had first the Honor of Attending upon him, During this Retreat, whilst Mr. <hi>Whitgrave,</hi> his Lady and Mother, (who alone of all the Houshold were Privy to the Secret) were often busied in watching and other discharges of their Duty towards his Accommodation and Safeguard, His Majesty was pleased to entertain himself for the most part with me in my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, by perusing several of my Books, amongst others he took up this present Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise then a Manuscript, lying on the Table of a Closet adjacent to my Chamber. He read it; He seriously considered it, and after mature deliberation pronounced this Sentence upon it, (viz) <hi>I have not seen any thing more Plain and Clear up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Subject: The Arguments here drawn from Succession, are so conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive, I do not conceive how they can be denyed.</hi> Now that this was not any sudden motion or superficial Complement of his Majesty, but the Product of a Real and Solid Conviction, is manifest by the Tenor and gravity of the words them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; by the Papers found in his Closet after his Decease under his own hand, which seem even to the very manner of expression to breath the same Spirit and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius with that of the Book: And lastly, by those truly Christian Catholic Resolutions he took (albeit through frailty late) in disposing himself for an happy departure out of this World by an entire Reconcilement to God and the Church. For this Cause I have annexed to the close of this Treatise as well the beforementioned Papers, as also a brief Account of what upon my own knowledg occured at his Death in regard to Religion. If therefore evincing Arguments, confirmed by the final Sentiments and Example of a King known as great in Judgment as Dignity, may through the Influence of Divine Grace, be Prevalent: I have just Reason to hope this little Book will have the same effect upon others as it had upon him. The sole Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the Present Edition.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40980:5"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Short and plain Way to the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Church.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ALMIGHTY God, who (as St.
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Aug. in Manu, cap. 1.</note>
               <hi>Augustin</hi> well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serveth) <hi>tho' he change his Work, alters not his Design;</hi> having from all Eternity decreed to bring Man to his final End and Happiness by <hi>Obedience;</hi> What he ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted not in the first <hi>Adam,</hi> he accomplisht in the <hi>Second;</hi> whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> made
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Heb. 5. v. 9.</note>
               <hi>Author of Eternal Salvation to all that obey him,</hi> and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rve his Law; for God hath proposed him <hi>a Propitiation by Faith,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And therefore in his Eternal Providence, ordaining a <hi>lively <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Faith,</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">For in Christ Jesus neither Circumcision, nor uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cision availeth any thing, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith, which worketh by Charity, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 6. Without Faith it is impossible to please <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 6. All the Prophets witness that through his Name, all that believe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im shall receive Remission of their Sins, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 43. The just Man liveth by Faith. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>om.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 17.</note> as the chiefest means whereby we are to work out our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lvation, he hath essentially implied in the exercise thereof, an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mble <hi>Subjection</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> of our <hi>Ʋnderstanding to his reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Will,</hi> so as the very Act of Belief, is in Holy Scripture often stiled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>Obedience.</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">All obey not the Gospel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 16. Who hath bewitched you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot to obey the truth, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 1. If any Man obey not the Word, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 14. Ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave obey'd from your very heart unto the form of Doctrin, whereunto you are deliver'd, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>om.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 7. Rendring Vengeance unto them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which obey not the Gospel of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ord, 2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 8. Who did let you, that you did not obey the Truth, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Wherefore Great assuredly and dangerous is their mistake, who in the Mysteries of Christian Religion, <hi>deny</hi> or <hi>doubt,</hi> when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he dim light of Natural <hi>Reason</hi> affords them no clear apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of the Object: Seeing God in these affairs, (through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merit of our first
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Being inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 5. You shall be as Gods, knowing Good and Evil.</note> Transgression) exacteth from our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, rather by a submissive
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Unless you believe, you shall not understand, <hi>Is.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 9. according to the Translation of the <hi>Septuagint.</hi> Not quickness of Understanding, but simplicity of belief maketh the people or vulgar sort most secure, <hi>Aug. contr. Epist. Fund. c.</hi> 4.</note> Faith, to <hi>give</hi> assent, then by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he light of Natural Reason, to <hi>receive</hi> satisfaction.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For so great is Mans inbred desire to <hi>know,</hi> and even in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40980:6"/> State of Innocence, so nearly bordering upon excess; that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> crafty
<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 5. The Serpent said to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> what day shall you Eat thereof your Eyes shall be opened, and you shall be as Gods knowing Good a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Evil, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 3. But I fear, as the Serpent seduced <hi>Eve</hi> by his subtility; So yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Senses may be corrupted, and you fall from that Simplicity which is in <hi>Jesus</hi> Christ.</note>
               <hi>Serpent</hi> thought it his best advantage, to assail us in that u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>satiable Appetite of <hi>Knowledge;</hi> our own inclination, (natural<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> prone thereunto) seeming to his malignant subtility the fittest <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ass</hi> to draw us to his design'd mark, our Everlasting Destruction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. But the Wisdom of our Heavenly Physician, perceiving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to surfeit on that <hi>forbidden fruit,</hi> contrived a Remedy opposite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Disease, curing that excessive desire to know, by prescribe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> abstinence from curious search of his Mysteries; and in just p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nishment of the Minds,
<note place="margin">The search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Majesty shall be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed with Glory, <hi>Prov.</hi> 25. <hi>vers.</hi> 27. Search not things higher than thy reach, neither seek the things which are too mighty for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> But what God hath commanded, think upon that with Reverence, and be not cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious in many of his Works, — for it is not needful for thee to see with thine Eye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> those things that are hidden; for many things are shewed thee, above the Capacit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Men, and the medling with such hath beguiled many, and an Evil Opinion hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deceived the Judgment, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 21, 22, 23, 24.</note> Rebellion
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Bringing into Captivity <hi>eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (thought) or</hi> Understanding to the Obedience of Christ, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 5.</note> captivating it to an obs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quious belief of things not appearing and unsearchable: Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what Pride of Wit and Reason had lost, might be regained, by a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> humble Obedience of Faith; and the Mind believing stedfastly what it cannot clearly understand, might better satisfie for Rebe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lious affectation of Knowledge.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Wherefore God having ordained (as before I said) a <hi>superna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tural Faith,</hi> so absolutely necessary to Salvation as without it<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 28. <hi>Acts</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 43. See <hi>Numb.</hi> 2.</note> non<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can be saved, and furthermore (on his part) earnestly desiring<note n="(k)" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 4.</note>
               <hi>tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all should be saved and come to the knowledge of the Truth;</hi> his infinit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Goodness and Providence,<note n="(l)" place="margin">To them who do what they are able God denyeth not his aid, a common Axiom amongst Divines. God would have none to perish, but would have all men to come to Repentance, 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 3. <hi>verse</hi> 9.</note> (never forsaking his Creatures in ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cessaries,) hath undoubtedly provided some<note n="(m)" place="margin">See <hi>Is.</hi> 35. throughout, but particularly <hi>verse</hi> 8. where Almighty God promiseth that there shall be a path and way, and it shall be called the Holy Way, and it shall be so direct or plain a way <hi>(to us)</hi> as even fools cannot err in it.</note> assured way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> means, by which all may sufficiently know, and so obedien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> embrace saving Faith.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Which <hi>Faith,</hi> or supernatural Knowledge, being it self<note n="(n)" place="margin">Faith is the substance of thing hoped for, the Argument of things not appearing, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 1. We see now as by a glass in dark sort, but then face to face; now I know in part, but then I shall know, as I am known, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 12.</note>
               <hi>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>scure,</hi> and of things far transcending the Sphere of human capacity
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40980:6"/> and yet by Divine Ordinance to be obtained <hi>by</hi>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. How shall they believe in him, of whom they have not heard? How shall they hear without a Preacher? how shall they preach unless they be sent? <hi>&amp;c. ver.</hi> 14, 15. Then Faith is by hearing, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. v.</hi> 17.</note>
               <hi>Hearing,</hi> it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oweth necessarily, that there must be some (to us certainly known <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd) undoubted<note n="(p)" place="margin">See this proved at large, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14. following; <q rend="margQuotes">If Gods Providence govern human affairs, saith St. <hi>Aug.</hi> we must not despair or doubt, but that he hath ordained some cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Authority, upon which staying our selves, as upon a certain ground or step, we may be lifted up to God, <hi>Aug. utilit. Credendi.</hi>
                  </q>
               </note> Authority, which may deliver as from God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ose things wherein he thus exacteth our Belief, upon which <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hority,</hi> as upon a certain Ground, or Basis, while we rely, we may be raised up to the necessary knowledge, love and service of his Sovereign Majesty.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Now this <hi>Authority</hi> must neither be <hi>divine only,</hi> nor <hi>only hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> but <hi>human inspired by God:</hi> Not <hi>only human,</hi> in regard of the<note n="(q)" place="margin">Error &amp; tenebrae pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus concre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ata sunt, <hi>Eccli. c.</hi> 11.16. Error and darkness had their beginning together with sinners. For the thoughts of mortal men are fearful, and our forecasts are uncertain, because a corruptible Body is burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>som to the Soul, and the earthly Mansion presseth down the—mind that is full of cares; hardly can we discern the things that are upon Earth, and with great labor find we out the things, that are before us; but who can seek out the things that are in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; or who can know thy Counsel (O God) except thou give him Wisdom, and send thy Holy Spirit from above? for so the ways of them that are upon Earth are made streight, and Men are taught the things that are pleasing unto thee, and are preserved through thy Wisdom, <hi>Sap.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14, <hi>&amp;c. Is.</hi> 40. <hi>v.</hi> 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 29. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 16. See the Book of Wisdom, Prot. Translation, in the places mentioned.</note> Weakness, Ignorance and Error of Mans Understanding, even in things natural and of inferior Alloy: Whereas the knowledge of that saving Truth, must be <hi>certain</hi> and <hi>infallible,</hi> of matters hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly and supernatural.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Neither must it be <hi>Divine alone</hi> without the Ministry of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Authority,</hi> appointed to that end by God, in regard his infinite Wisdom doth not ordinarily
<note n="(r)" place="margin">This is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at large by St. <hi>Aug.</hi> in the Preface of his Book of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Doctrin,</hi> both by Reason and Divine Authority: Where he thus concludeth; <q rend="margQuotes"> How should it be true which is said, <hi>The Temple of God is Holy, which you are,</hi> if God would pronounce, and give no answer from this Temple, but all which Men should learn he would deliver from Heaven or by Angels?</q> This Truth is also expresly confessed and taught by <hi>Calvin, Inst. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>sect.</hi> 5. Where he says, <q rend="margQuotes">We see that God who could in a moment perfect his Elect, would notwithstanding that they should not grow to their full strength, but by Education of the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For this purpose it was his Will, that in times past there should be sacred Metings at the Sanctuary, that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins pronounced by the Mouth of the Priest, might nourish or increase the Consent or Unity of Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and as he did not send them before the Gospel, to learn of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, but raised them Teachers from the Earth, who might truly perform that Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Function; So his Will is at this day, that we should teach in a manner agreeabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to Mans Nature; and as formerly he was not content with the Law alone, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Priests, Interpreters,</hi> from whom the people might inquire, or receive the Sens<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or meaning thereof; So in these times also.</q> Thus <hi>Calvin.</hi> And Bishop <hi>Bancroft,</hi> in his Sermon preached the 8th of <hi>February,</hi> saith <q rend="margQuotes">God hath bound himself to his Church, of purpose, that Men by her good direction might in matters of doubt be relieved.</q>
               </note> teach us the Mysteries of Faith, in that manner; as appeareth by the <hi>Law, Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Gospel,</hi> throughout; so expounded as to this particular, even by our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:40980:7"/>10. To what may be objected, <hi>Isa.</hi> 54. <hi>v.</hi> 13. <hi>All shall be taught of God;</hi> and Jerem. 31. v. 34. <hi>Every one shall no more Teach his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> &amp;c. We answer briefly; it is the manner of Holy Scripture, in such things as are principally wrought by God, to speak as if he alone wrought them, without <hi>Means</hi> or <hi>Instrument,</hi> that all Glory may be given to him alone, who imparts to the Instrument its force and aptness to co-operate.</p>
            <p n="11">11. This <hi>certain Authority</hi> therefore, by which <hi>all</hi> at <hi>all times</hi> may be sufficiently directed, and resolved in all Points of Faith, as by an External, Competent and Infallible Judge, cannot be the <hi>Written Word alone,</hi> as Protestants affirm.</p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>First,</hi> in regard it is <hi>obscure,</hi> both for the<note n="(s)" place="margin">O wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of thy words! won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundness, O my God, it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a Man tremble to look upon it, St. <hi>Aug. in Confes. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. O the depth of the Wisdom and Knowledge of God! how incomprehensible are his Judgments, and unsearchable his ways? <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33.</note>
               <hi>depth of matters,</hi> contained, and <hi>manner of delivering</hi> them; <hi>Dark, Ambiguous, Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorical: Secondly,</hi> it expresseth not <hi>all matters of Faith,</hi> as, what Books are Scripture? What not? That God commanded the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath to be changed; that there are two Natures in Christ, and <hi>but one Person, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That Authority which is <hi>Supream Judge</hi> in <hi>doubtful affairs,</hi> must <hi>necessarily</hi> be such, as, with <hi>all</hi> who acknowledge and receive it in that kind, it may be able <hi>clearly</hi> and <hi>efficaciously</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin, <hi>all</hi> their Controversies; but Scripture alone is not able to do this, in all<note n="(t)" place="margin">
                  <hi>See before,</hi> Numb. 12 <hi>And to the instances thereof, may be added, that</hi> such as are baptised by Heretics ought not to be rebaptized, <hi>That</hi> the blessed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was a perpetual Virgin, <hi>yea,</hi> that the Holy Ghost is one Substance with the Father and the Son.</note> controverted Points of Religion; for it doth not in all of them clearly pronounce Sentence, nay, even <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans,</hi> and <hi>Calvinists, Anabaptists</hi> and <hi>Arians,</hi> (who acknowledge it for Judge) after whatsoever is therein pronounced, continue still in their violent and virulent<note n="(u)" place="margin">The Dissentions that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, <hi>saith</hi> Nich. Gallus <hi>a Protestant,</hi> are not light, nor of light, but of chief Articles of Christian Doctrin, as of the Law and the Gospel, of Justification and Good Works, of the Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c. Thus</hi> Nich. Gallus in Thess. &amp; Hypoth. <hi>He might have added with</hi> Selucer, <hi>upon the</hi> 103. Psal. part 3d. <hi>Their Dissention about the</hi> Humanity of Christ, <hi>his</hi> As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention into Heaven, and sitting on the Right Hand of God, <hi>&amp;c. And here in</hi> England, about his descent into Hell, Predestination, <hi>and the</hi> necessity of Bishops in the Church: We, <hi>saith</hi> Martin Luther, censure in good earnest the <hi>Zuinglians,</hi> and all Sacramentarians, (that is, all who deny the real and substantial Presence of Christs Body in the Sacrament) for Heretics and Aliens from the Church of God: <hi>Luth. cont. Articul Lovan. Thes.</hi> 27. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 53.</note> altercations: No party confessing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40980:7"/> Scripture to have given Sentence against them. Whereas, the Judge should so pronounce Sentence, as the one Party may know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves condemn'd, the other clear'd: else there can be no end of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spute and contention. <hi>Lastly,</hi> in all well ordered Common-wealths, besides the <hi>Law</hi> under which the People live, there must be some <hi>external Judge,</hi> to expound and declare (with irrefragable Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) the <hi>Sense</hi> and <hi>true meaning</hi> of the Law; much more in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Kingdom of Christ, where the Law is more <hi>profound</hi> and <hi>difficult,</hi> the Errors more <hi>dangerous;</hi> Subjection, Unity, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Governours more <hi>Necessary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. We conclude therefore, that the <hi>True Church of God, or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates thereof,</hi> assisted by his Word and<note n="(w)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Is.</hi> 59 <hi>v.</hi> 21. My Spirit which is in thee, and my words which I have put in thy Mouth shall not depart from thy Mouth, and from the Mouth of thy Seed, and from the Mouth of thy Seeds Seed, saith our Lord, from henceforth for ever: <hi>Where God promiseth, saith</hi> Calvin, that the Church shall always be govern'd by the Holy Ghost. <hi>Calv.</hi> upon the 59th. <hi>ch.</hi> of <hi>Is.</hi> I will ask the Father, and he will give you another Paraclyte, that he may abide with you for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, even the Spirit of Truth, <hi>John</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 16. When the Spirit of Truth cometh, he will teach you all Truth, <hi>John</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 13. <hi>Iren. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Advers. Haeres. c.</hi> 4. If any Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion arise, ought we not, <hi>saith he,</hi> to have recourse to the most ancient Churches, and take from them, concerning the present doubt, that wich is certain and clear? <hi>And</hi> Tertul. de Praescript. cap. 21. <hi>saith,</hi> What the Apostles preached, that is, what Christ re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to them; here also I will prescribe, that it ought not otherwise to be proved, but by the same Churches, which the Apostles founded. <hi>And</hi> Irenaeus, <hi>in the place before alledged, yieldeth a reason,</hi> viz. That the Apostles most fully laid up all Truth in the Church, as in a Rich Treasure-house. <hi>See the like in St.</hi> Aug. Tom. 7. contra Crescon. lib. 1. cap. 33.</note> Spirit, and perpetually, by Succession of Bishops and Pastors, present to the Faithful in all Times and Ages, is the <hi>sole appointed external Propounder</hi> and <hi>Expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> of his <hi>Law,</hi> or (in a General Council) <hi>Infallible Judge</hi> of <hi>Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versies</hi> in Religion: otherwise how should we be undoubtedly assured, that former Heresies were rightly condemned?</p>
            <p n="15">15. In which respect the Eternal Wisdom of God, plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth of the Priests and Pastors of the Church, that they shall Teach his People, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in Controversie they shall stand to Judge, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44. <hi>v.</hi> 23, 24. Also <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. from <hi>ver.</hi> 8. to 14. <hi>If thou perceive thy Judgment with thee be hard and doubtful,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thou shalt come to the Priests, of the Levitical Stock,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and thou shalt ask of them the Truth of the Judgment, and thou shalt do whatsoever they,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>shall say and teach according to the Law, and thou shalt follow their Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, neither shalt thou decline to the Right Hand or to the Left, but he that shall be proud, refusing to obey the Commandment of the Priest, that Man shall die,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus far Almighty God ordaining a <hi>Supream Tribunal,</hi> for reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of doubtful affairs (even in matters of Religion) from which there ought to be no <hi>appeal,</hi> as learned<note n="(x)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds in Cons. p. 251. Whitt. de Sacr. Script. p. 466. Bilson Perp. Gover. p. 20. Hooker Pref. Eccl. Pol. p. 26, 27, 28.</note> Protestants them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40980:8"/> confess. Which <hi>Decree,</hi> in the first and principal Intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being <hi>Moral,</hi> was not abolished by Cessation of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Observances, yea rather (in effect) it is often ratified and confirmed in the New and Old Testament, so far as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the <hi>Sovereign Power</hi> of Gods Church for Determination of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical Controversies, namely, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 17. where Christ in case of like<note n="(y)" place="margin">Like, I mean, to that expressed, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. in the place before alledg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed. Christ, as he provided here against other differences of the faithful, so especially, for those in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Doctrin, as more perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to his Church; see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugn the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation thereof, Unity of Faith and Religion, <hi>One God, one Faith,</hi> Eph. 4. (Observe here.)</note> Dispute with our Brother, commandeth us to <hi>tell the Church,</hi> adding, <hi>if he will not hear the Church, let him be unto thee as a Heathen and a Publican,</hi> that is, (without further Appeal) separated from the Communion of Saints; also <hi>Malachy</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>The Lips of the Priest shall keep Knowledge, and they shall require the Law from his Mouth, for he is the Angel of the Lord of Hosts;</hi> Luk. 10. v. 16. <hi>He that heareth you, heareth me; he that despiseth you, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiseth me,</hi> and 1 John 4. <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>He that is of God heareth us; he that is not of God hearerh us not, in this we know the Spirit of Truth and the Spirit of Error:</hi> Also Rom. 10. v. 14. <hi>How shall they believe in him, of whom they have not heard? How shall they hear without a Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? And how shall they preach unless they be sent?</hi> Faith therefore cometh <hi>by hearing</hi> the Pastors of Gods Church: And observe the Apostles Gradation; no <hi>Faith,</hi> but by <hi>hearing;</hi> no <hi>hearing,</hi> but by preaching; no <hi>preaching</hi> without Mission or lawful <hi>Calling</hi> by God and his Church: Also, Heb. 5. v. 1. Heb. 13. v. 17. <hi>Obey your Prelates and be subject unto them, for they watch as they that must give an account for your Souls.</hi> Lastly, Christ ascending into Heaven, saith the Apostle, gave therefore, <hi>viz.</hi> to his Church, and as it were in his place) <hi>Some Apostles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephes. 4.11.</note>
               <hi>some Prophets, some Evangelists, and some Pastors and Teachers; for the work of the Ministry, and building up the Mystical Body of Christ, till we all meet in the Ʋnity of Faith,</hi> &amp;c. That is, even as learned<note n="(z)" place="margin">Calv. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stit. lib 4. c. 8. sect. 37, 38. Melanct. Loc. com. cap. 1. de Eccl. Fulk a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Rhemes Test. hereupon, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes. 4.</note> Protestants expound, until the end of the World: and declaring in the same place the design or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of God herein, <hi>ver.</hi> 14. he addeth, that <hi>We may henceforth be no more as Children wavering, and carried about with every wind of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, by the deceipt of Men, and with Craftiness, whereby they lay wait to deceive:</hi> so manifestly doth the Spirit of God here by St. <hi>Paul</hi> declare, that he hath ordained the Pastors of his Church to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Truth unto us, and preserve us from wavering or fluctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating in Faith.</p>
            <p n="16">16. It now remaineth to shew which is the True Church, to the end, that having found out that <hi>Pillar of Faith,</hi> that <hi>immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Spouse of Christ,</hi> we may embrace her <hi>Doctrin,</hi> obey her <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees,</hi> and repose securely in her <hi>Judgments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. Wherefore observe diligently, the Question in this matter betwixt us, and our Adversaries, is not <hi>what</hi> is the true Church? But <hi>which</hi> is the true Church? That is, we enquire not here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the intrinsical Essence of the Church: But by what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and sensible Notes, Signs or Marks, we may find out and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40980:8"/> discover which, amongst so many pretended Faithful Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, is the <hi>True Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. Protestants assign as marks<note n="(a)" place="margin">Whitg. Defen. p. 81. Willet Synop. p. 69. Confes. August. Artic. 7. Calv. Instit. lib. 4. cap. 1. sect. 10. Church of England Artic. 19. Prop. 4. <hi>See the Book intituled,</hi> The Catholic Doctrin of the Church of England, pag. 92. <hi>allowed by public Authority.</hi>
               </note> whereby to find out the true Church, <hi>Lawful Ministry of the Word and Sacraments;</hi> but impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, and not without fraud.</p>
            <p n="19">19. For the Mark and Note whereby any thing (to us unknown) is to be discovered and found out, must be first known, and more evident then what we seek thereby to note or discover: Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise we shall not find what we seek, but vainly endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve one matter in doubt, by another more or equally doubtful and intricate.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Whereas, first, <hi>Lawful Ministry of the Word,</hi> or <hi>Truth of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin</hi> is more unknown to us, than the <hi>Church</hi> which is always vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, and therefore in the Holy Scripture compared unto <hi>a</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 14, 15. Ye are the light of the World: A Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty set on a Hill, cannot be hid; neither do Men light a Candle and put it under a Bushel <hi>(of invisibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty);</hi> but on a Candlestic, that it may shine to all.</note>
               <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on a Hill; a</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 5. He hath placed his tabernacle in the Sun. That— is, <hi>saith St.</hi> August. <hi>there,</hi> his Church in public, not in private.</note>
               <hi>Tabernacle in the Sun, a</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Is. c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 2. In the latter days there shall be prepared a Mountain, in the tops of Mountains, and it shall be lifted above the Hills, and all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions shall flow unto it, and many people shall say, come let us go up to the Mountain of our Lord, to the House of the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and he will teach us his ways, and we will walk in his paths: For the Law shall go out of <hi>Sion,</hi> and the word of the Lord from <hi>Jerusalem. So plain it is, that first we are to repair to the House of God, and there to learn his Law and Word. See St.</hi> August. Tract. 1. Epist. Joan, &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>Mountain on the top of Mountains,</hi> and expresly affirmed to be<note n="(e)" place="margin">Isa. cap. 35. ver. 8.</note>
               <hi>a path way so direct or plain, as even Fools do not,</hi> (or cannot) <hi>Err therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21. Secondly. None may Preach (that is, Teach as <hi>Pastor,</hi>) the Word, and Administer the Sacraments, according to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary course appointed by God, unless they be Lawfully<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 6.</note>
               <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained,</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 14, 15, 16. How shall they hear without a Preacher? how shall they preach, unless they be sent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Sent</hi> and <hi>Called</hi> thereunto by the Church: Therefore the Church must first be known, and by the Church their Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Calling to that Ministry; for <hi>Faith cometh by hearing,</hi> Rom. 10. <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>Hearing by the Word of God,</hi> and this from the Pastors Lawfully Ordained, Sent or Called by God's Church: Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church therefore we must first repair to know whom we ought to <hi>hear,</hi> that so <hi>hearing</hi> we may <hi>believe,</hi> and believing obtain <hi>Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="22">22. Thirdly. We know not certainly the Books of Scripture
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40980:9"/> but by the Church,<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <hi>St.</hi> Aug. Tom. 6. contr. Epist. Fund. c. 5. <hi>saith,</hi> I would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, unless the Authority of the Church moved me thereto; <hi>Also Mr.</hi> Hooker, <hi>a Protestant, plainly affirmeth,</hi> that it is confessed impossible for Scripture it self to teach what Books are Divine, Eccles. Pol. lib. 3.14.</note> much less the Sense and true meaning of them; Wherefore doubting Souls in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> desiring to know <hi>where the Bridegroom feedeth,</hi> receive from the Spirit of God this Direction,<note n="(i)" place="margin">Cant. 1. v. 7.</note>
               <hi>If thou knowest not, get thee forth by the Steps of the Flocks, and feed thy Kids by the Tents of the Shepherds,</hi> directing (saith the Marginal note of the English Protestant Bible) <hi>the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to their Pastors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23. Fourthly. The certain knowledge of <hi>True Ministry of the Word,</hi> in that boundless Latitude, supposing a resolution, of all doubtful matters, of Faith, is a thing impossible, for most, (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure any of the Faithful,) to arrive unto; and a Man may sooner end his Life, than such an Inquiry, which according to that mark cannot be done, but by an entire knowledge of all Truth; and this, according to Protestants, by the Written Word alone, which multitudes cannot read, much less understand.</p>
            <p n="24">24. Fifthly. <hi>True Ministry of the Word,</hi> or <hi>Truth of Doctrin</hi> is the matter chiefly in question, and all grant that it may be learned most speedily by the <hi>True Church,</hi> which we therefore seek to know; so as to assign True Ministry of the Word, as a mark whereby to find out the True Church is in effect to assign the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter most in question for a resolution.</p>
            <p n="25">25. Sixthly. According to this mark the Reformed Churches (as they call them) of <hi>England, France, Germany, Holland, &amp;c</hi> are not the True Catholic Church; for all of them have not the Word <hi>truly preached,</hi> seeing they differ<note n="(k)" place="margin">See before at Numb. 13. in the Margin, where their Dissentions in these and the like matters are acknowledged by Protestants.</note> contradictorily in <hi>fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Points of Religion,</hi> as about the Books of Scripture, the Law and Gospel, Faith &amp; Works, Articles of the Creed and Sacraments.</p>
            <p n="26">26. Seventhly. Amongst <hi>Schismatics</hi> not fallen to formal He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie, but dividing themselves from the Church, (through Pride only and Disobedience,) there may be found the same Ministry of Doctrin and Sacraments with the True Church; yet are not Schismatics according to St. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               <note n="(l)" place="margin">No man can have Christ for Head who is not in his Body, which is the Church; Heritics by believing falsly of God, do violate the Faith, and Schismatics by their wicked dissentions, fly from fraternal Charity, altho' they believe as we do; and therefore neither doth the Heretic belong to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Church, because he believeth not God; nor the Schismatic, because he loveth not his Neighbor, <hi>Aug. de Unit. Eccles. c.</hi> 19.</note> members of the true Church.</p>
            <p n="27">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:40980:9"/>27. Lastly. It is against the Ordinance of God, in Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; where he prescribeth that we should receive the Word of Faith and his Law from the <hi>Pastors</hi> of his Church, as before<note n="(m)" place="margin">See the Text Numb. <hi>5, &amp;c.</hi> throughout.</note> we proved at large, and our<note n="(n)" place="margin">
                  <hi>See before in the Marginal Note of Numb.</hi> 9. <hi>what is there alledged out of</hi> Calvin, <hi>who in the same</hi> chap. sect. 5. <hi>stileth the Church</hi> a faithful keeper of the Truth, <hi>affirming that all true Doctrin is to be required from her Ministry. Dr.</hi> Field <hi>likewise, in his Preface to his first Book</hi> of the Church, <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viseth well, saying;</hi> For as much as Controversies in Religion in our time are grown in number so many, in nature so intricate, that few have time or leisure, fewer strength of understanding to examin them, what remaineth for Men desirous of satisfaction in things of such consequence, but diligently to serach out, which, amongst all the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties of Men in the World, is that blessed <hi>Company of Holy ones,</hi> that <hi>Houshold of Faith,</hi> that <hi>Spouse of Christ,</hi> and <hi>Church of the living God,</hi> which is the <hi>ground of Truth,</hi> that so we may embrace her Communion, follow her Direction and rest in her Judgment?</note> Adversaries convinc'd by Truth do plainly confess: The <hi>Church</hi> therefore of necessity must be the first known, and by the Church the Law and Doctrin of Christ.</p>
            <p n="28">28. Wherefore leaving this<note n="(o)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Fraudulent</hi> because assign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry of the Word or Truth of Doctrin, as the only Mark or Note, whereby we are to find out the true Church, howbeit more difficult and unknown to us, than the Church it self.</note> fraudulent Tergiversation of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, and omitting for brevity's sake, such Notes and Marks of the Catholic Church, as others usually do assign; I suppose first as evident in Gods Book, and acknowledged.</p>
            <p n="29">29. That the True Church must continue<note n="(p)" place="margin">In the days of those Kings shall the God of Heaven set up a Kingdom, which shall never be destroyed, and this Kingdom shall not be given to another People; but it shall break and destroy all other Kingdoms, and it self shall stand for ever, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 44. Of the Increase, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> On the Throne of <hi>David</hi> shall he sit to strengthen it, with Judgment and Justice from henceforth for ever: The Zeal of the Lord of Hosts will perform this, <hi>Is.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>See also,</hi> Luke 1. <hi>v.</hi> 33. Upon this Rock will I build my Church, and Hells Gates shall not prevail against it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 18. Behold I am with you all days, even to the consum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the World, <hi>Mat. ult.</hi>
               </note> for ever.</p>
            <p n="30">30. Secondly. (Which our Adversaries<note n="(q)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Whitta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, <hi>speaking of the necessary Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry of the Word and Sacraments, saith,</hi> They are essential Properties of the Church, <hi>contr. Dur. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 260. Being present they constitute a Church, being absent they subvert it, <hi>ib. p.</hi> 249. Deering <hi>upon the Epistle to the</hi> Hebrews, cap. 3. lect. 16. Take away Preaching, you take away Faith, the Ministry of the Word and Sacraments is in absolute degree of necessity to Salvation. <hi>Defens. of Eccles. Discip. p.</hi> 33. These Marks cannot be absent from the Church, and it is no longer a true Church than it hath them. <hi>Willet. Synop. p.</hi> 71. The only absence <hi>of them</hi> makes a Nullity to the Church.</note> likewise confess) that it cannot so continue without lawful Ministry of the Word and Sacraments.</p>
            <p n="31">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:40980:10"/>31. Thirdly. The Word and Sacraments, according to Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, cannot be ministred but by lawful
<note n="(r)" place="margin">No man ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to himself, but he that is called of God, as <hi>Aaron</hi> was, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4. How shall they preach unless they be sent? <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>See also Numb.</hi> 16. <hi>throughout,</hi> Acts 15. <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4. <hi>So as the Spirit of God in holy Scripture brandeth Hereticks with the marks of coming</hi> unsent, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. <hi>v.</hi> 21. I have not sent them, yet they ran. All that came before me are Thieves and Robbers, <hi>John</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>and in the same Chapter,</hi> Verily, verily. I say unto you, he that entereth not in by the Door (viz. <hi>by lawful Calling and Ordination</hi>) into the Sheepfold, but climeth up another way is a Thief and a Robber. <hi>This truth is likewise confessed by our Adversaries,</hi> Cartwright, <hi>in his</hi> Second Reply, part 2. p. 128. <hi>saith,</hi> It is forbidden that any should take this honor to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, but he who is called of God as <hi>Aaron</hi> was: What greater necessity of Sacrifice, than when <hi>Saul</hi> took it upon him? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. What greater appearance of necessity than when <hi>Ozias</hi> stayed the <hi>Ark</hi> ready to fall? 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 7. Yet these necessities notwithstanding, for so much as they took upon them, that, whereunto they were not called, they receiv'd the reward of their boldness. <hi>Thus far Mr.</hi> Cartwright <hi>in the place alledged.</hi>
               </note> Priests and Pastors.</p>
            <p n="32">32. Fourthly, That none can be lawful Priest and Pastors, except they be ordained by Bishops, and duly
<note n="(s)" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>This, to omit other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, is at large declared by</hi> Willet <hi>Protestant Bishop of</hi> Rochester, <hi>from Scriptures, Fathers, Councils and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the whole Church, in his Sermon preached at</hi> Hampton-Court, Sept. 21. 1606. <hi>when he saith, touching Ordination,</hi> That in the Church of <hi>Ephesus</hi> there were <hi>Presbyters</hi> long before <hi>Timothy</hi> was appointed Bishop there. Yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> sent him on purpose to impose Hands, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. and for that intent also he left <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Creta, Tit.</hi> 1.5. Neither would the Church of Christ succeeding admit any other but Bishops to that business, as not justifiable for the Presbyter, either by Reason, Example or Scripture; for Reason, it is a Rule without contradiction, <hi>saith the Apostle,</hi> Heb. 7. <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>That he which blesseth should be greater then he which is blessed,</hi> (taking it for the Blessing which is by <hi>Authority,</hi> not of Devotion;) The blessing of authority therefore come from the <hi>greater,</hi> as honor is in him that confers it, not in him that takes it, and this is St. <hi>Ambrose</hi> his Reason on 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. Secondly, for <hi>Example,</hi> not one is shewed through the Ecclesiastical History, that any besides a Bishop did it; if some of the Inferior presumed to do it, his Act was reversed by the Church as unlawful, as in the case of <hi>Colluthus</hi> a Presbyter of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> whereof St. <hi>Athanasius</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius</hi> make mention, who took upon him to give Orders, for which both himself was censured and what he did was revoked, and they received as meer Lay-men, and no otherwise, into the Communion, whom he had ordered: For <hi>Scripture,</hi> there is none, neither of holy Men, nor of the Holy Ghost; for all the holy Fathers with one consent do contradict it. <hi>Chrys.</hi> upon 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.4. <hi>Theodoret</hi> upon the same places, <hi>Oecumenius</hi> upon 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5 <hi>Ambrose</hi> is peremptory, that it is neither <hi>fas</hi> nor <hi>jus,</hi> consonant neither with God's nor Man's Law, that any besides a Bishop should do it. Yea <hi>Hierome</hi> himself, who setteth a Presbyter on his Tip-toes, to make him go equal with a Bishop, yet takes him this one Peg down, <hi>excepta Ordinatione:</hi> Wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is it saith he, that a Bishop doth that a Presbyter may not do, saving Ordination? No Scripture of the Holy Ghost either analogically by consequence, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly by Precept: For <hi>Analogy,</hi> none but the Apostles did it, or might do it (as before you heard) not <hi>directly,</hi> for to what Presbyter was the Authority committed, as to a Presbyter only? Unto <hi>Timothy</hi> a Bishop of <hi>Ephesus</hi> it was said, <hi>Lay hands hastily on no Man,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. and to <hi>Titus</hi> a Bishop of <hi>Creta, I have left thee to ordain Presbyters, T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 1.5.</p>
                  <p>Thus far the Protestant Bishop of <hi>Rochester,</hi> in his Sermon printed by King <hi>James</hi>'s Commandment, where he also answereth the Doubts and Objections to the contrary. See likewise Bishop <hi>Bonner</hi> in his <hi>Survey</hi> of the pretended Discipline, <hi>c.</hi> 8. throughout▪ <hi>Whitgift</hi> his <hi>Defen. Hook. Eccles. Pol. Cowel</hi> his <hi>Defence of Hooker.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> called to the Function.</p>
            <p n="33">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:40980:10"/>33. All which supposed, I prove the Protestant Church not to be the True Church of God. For,</p>
            <p n="34">34. The true Church of God must continue ever, but the Protestant Church hath not
<note n="(t)" place="margin">A particular Church, tho' it hath not been, or continued at all times Catholic, yet for the time that it is a true Church, it must of necessity communicate in Profession of the same Faith, and Sacraments, with that Church which from the Apostles time hath so continued in all Ages, otherwise it is not truly <hi>Catholic,</hi> and by reason of such Communion in Religion with Catholic &amp; Apostolic Churches, it may be said to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ever, as one with them in Profession of the same Faith &amp; Religion, which have been at all times conspicuous; howbeit in respect of some time, place or persons it is truly stiled a particular Church. The Apostles (saith <hi>Tertullian</hi>) founded Churches in every City, (<hi>viz.</hi> by themselves or others,) from these Churches thus founded, other Churches have and daily do borrow their Propagation of Faith, and Seed of Doctrin, by which they are Churches; and in this respect they also shall be reputed <hi>Apostolical,</hi> as Off-springs of Apostolical Churches, for every Off-spring must be reduced to his Original: Wherefore all those Churches shall be one first and Apostolical, from which they all descend, so long as all of them hold and approve the same Unity. <hi>Tertul. Prescript..</hi>
               </note> ever continued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Protestant Church is not the true Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="35">35. The Proposition before
<note n="(u)" place="margin">See Numb. 29 the Marg.</note> is clearly deduced out of Holy Scripture, the Assumption thus I prove.</p>
            <p>No Church can from age to age continue without
<note n="(w)" place="margin">See Numb. 29, 30, 31, 32. Without Bishops no Priests, without Priests no Ministers of the Word and Sacraments without these no Church.</note> perpetual Succession of Bishops.</p>
            <p>But the Protestant Church
<note n="(x)" place="margin">By Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Church we understand a Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of such Bps, Priests and People, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess the Faith now currant in <hi>England.</hi> See the Definition of a Church by a Protestant, <hi>Artic.</hi> 10. in the Book called <hi>Catholick Doctrine of the Church of</hi> England; for Faith and Religion are the Essential Difference, Form and Soul of the Church, so as where these are not one and the same, there the Church and Congregations are not one and the same, as with the Roman Catholics and Protestants, for they can make no claim to our Church and Bishops, but are engaged to shew a perpetual Succession of Bishops professing their own Faith and Religion. See before Numb. 34. they must shew their own Cards, not ours, if they mean to win the Game.</note> hath not had a perpetual Successi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Bishops.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="36">36. The Protestant Church hath not from age to age continued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not the true Church of God, which must continue ever.</p>
            <p n="37">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:40980:11"/>37. That Protestants have not had a <hi>perpetual Succession</hi> of their Bishops in former ages, is manifest, for let them<note n="(y)" place="margin">We stand not on the Name <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant,</hi> but exact Bishops ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be of the same Doctrin and Discipline. <hi>Tertul. Prascr. c.</hi> 3. Let them shew, <hi>saith he,</hi> the beginning of their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, let them unfold the Order of their Bishops, so by Succession coming down, as that the first Bishop have some of the Apostles or Apostolical Men, who yet perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with the Apostles, for his Author and Predecessor. Number, <hi>saith August.</hi> the Priests, or Bishops, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom the Seat it self of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and see in that Order of Fathers, who to whom hath succeeded; that is the Rock against which the proud Gates of Hell shall not prevail; <hi>Aug. in Psal. contr. Donat.</hi> and in another place he saith, The Order begun by <hi>Peter</hi> the Apostle, and even unto this Age, by the Propagation or Off spring of succeeding Bishops continued, they, <hi>viz.</hi> Heretics, interrupt, challeng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to themselves an Order without Original, <hi>August. Quest. Nov. &amp; Vet. Testam. Quest.</hi> 100.</note> name, if they can, so many as but three, known and acknowledged Protestant Bishops, succeeding each other in any part of the World, for the space of a <hi>thousand years</hi> next before <hi>Luther,</hi> by whom their Pastors were ordained; their Word and Sacraments administred; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils celebrated, Heresies condemned, Laws, Ordinances and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons enacted. But no ancient Monuments, Dipticks or Church-Rolls; No Histories Ecclesiastical or Profane make mention of any such continued Succession in former times of professed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Bishops, that is, Bishops distinct from our Roman Bishops, and professing the public Doctrin of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time.</p>
            <p>Secondly. If they had such Bishops, at the least twenty years before <hi>Luther,</hi> why did they not joyn with him, and follow his Followers, when they first opposed our Religion, in <hi>Germany,</hi> and other places?</p>
            <p>Thirdly. This known want of Protestant Bishops in former Ages, is a matter so manifest as they themselves acknowledge, their Church for many Ages before <hi>Luther</hi>
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">Before the days of <hi>Luther, saith</hi> Perkins, for the space of many hundred years, an universal Apostacy overspread the whole face of the Earth, and our (<hi>viz.</hi> Protestant) Church was not then visible to the World, <hi>Perkin</hi> upon the Creed, <hi>p.</hi> 400. and Mr. <hi>Nappier</hi> upon the <hi>Revelations, p.</hi> 143. confidently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verreth, that for 1260 years the Pope and his Clergy hath possessed the outward visible Church of Christians, reigning universally, and without any debateable contradiction, <hi>Nap. ibid. p.</hi> 68. God's true Church, <hi>saith he.</hi> most certainly abiding, so long latent and invisible, <hi>ibid. p.</hi> 191. and 161. and <hi>Sebastian Franc. de abrogat. in Univers Stat. Eccles.</hi> yet more plainly averreth, that for certain through the work of Antichrist, the external Church together with the Faith and Sacraments vanished shortly after the <hi>Apostles</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, and for these 1400 years the Church (<hi>viz.</hi> Protestant) hath been no where external and visible, <hi>Sebast. Fran. ibid</hi> and Mr. <hi>Jewel</hi> saith the true Church was unknown and unheard of, when <hi>Martin Luther</hi> and <hi>Zuinglius</hi> first came to the knowledge and preaching of the Gospel, <hi>Jewel Apol, part.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>divis.</hi> 2.</note> to have been <hi>invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:40980:11"/>
            <p>Fourthly. They yet confess that <hi>Luther</hi> had no right Believers<note n="(a)" place="margin">George Millius in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicat. conf. Aug. art. 1.7. de Eccles. pag. 137, 138.</note> before him from whom he might receive his Doctrin, and that it is ridiculous to think otherwise; considering, say they,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Benedic. Morganstern. Tract de Eccles. p. 143.</note> that it is manifest to the whole World, that before <hi>Luthers</hi> time, all Churches were overspread with more than <hi>Cymerian</hi> darkness: And <hi>Calvin</hi> affirmeth,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Calvin. Epist. 141. pag. 237 cum decessionem a toto mundo facere coacti sumus.</note>
               <hi>he made a revòlt</hi> or decession <hi>from the whole world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly. In regard of this their apparent want of Bishops, and want of lawful Ordination by them, they are constrained, either to challenge <hi>extraordinary</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Lascicius <hi>in proof of his own Opinion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth</hi> Calvin, <hi>saying,</hi> Because through the Popes Tyranny, the true course of Ordination was broken off, we stood in need of a new supply, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and this Calling was altogether extraordinary, Lascic. de Russ. Mosco. &amp; Tartar. Relig. <hi>See also</hi> Calvin. Instit. lib. 4. cap. 3 sect. 24. Cartwright <hi>against</hi> Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gift, pag. 217.</note>
               <hi>Calling,</hi> without Attestation of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, wherewith that Calling hath ever been accompanied,<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Exod. 4. John 15.22. Mark 16.20.</note> or else<note n="(f)" place="margin">This doth Mr. <hi>Mason</hi> in his Preface to his Book <hi>of Consecration of Bishops</hi> expresly acknowledge, by other Protestant Countries, <hi>England</hi> only excepted.</note> Ordination from Presbyters, that is inferior Ministers, who, as we<note n="(g)" place="margin">See before Numb. 32.</note> shewed before, from Gods Word, the Primitive Church and confession of Protestants, have no Power to ordain.</p>
            <p n="38">38. Neither will it suffice Protestants, for proof of the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of their Church, to avouch the precedent Succession of our Bishops, considering they generally maintain, that <hi>Doctrin or true Ministry of the Word and Sacraments</hi> are absolute and<note n="(h)" place="margin">Whitgift Defens. p. 181. Willet Synops. pag. 169. Whittak. cont. Dur. pag. 260. Confes. Aug. Art. 9 See also the Book intituled, <hi>The Catholic Doctrin of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>Art.</hi> 20. Where it defineth the Church to be a visible Congregation of faithful People, where the pure Word of God is preached, and Sacraments duly administred. And where, I pray, under the Cope of Heaven will Protestants find such a <hi>visible Congregation</hi> twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years immediately before <hi>Luther,</hi> or <hi>Waldo</hi> at least?</note> essential marks of the true Church, and consequently as these are not one and the same, but rather contradictorily opposite in our Church and theirs, so neither can our Church and theirs, nor the Succession of our Bishops, prove a continuance of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Church; they must shew their own Cards and not ours, if they mean to win the Game.</p>
            <p n="39">39. And for their Succession in <hi>England</hi> in precedent Ages, (to omit an inductive Remonstrance to the contrary) (by our<note n="(i)" place="margin">Mat. Paris Westm. &amp;c. <hi>Dr.</hi> Harpsf. <hi>pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Ballance.</hi>
               </note> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and modern Historiographers) Mr.<note n="(k)" place="margin">Mason <hi>in the Book mentioned in the Consecration of</hi> Matt. Park. p. <hi>131. saith,</hi> This was his singular felicity, that he being the 70th Arch-Bishop <hi>(of Canterbury)</hi> after <hi>St. Austin,</hi> yet of that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber he was the only Man and first of all who was consecrated without the Popes Bulls and superfluous <hi>Aaronical</hi> Garments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Mason</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40980:12"/> Author of <hi>Matthew Parker</hi>'s Life (more boldly than discreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) boasts, that the said <hi>Parker</hi> being the 70th Arch-Bishop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> after St. <hi>Austin</hi> our Apostle) of all that number he was the only Man who was consecrated without the Popes Bulls; all the rest therefore at their Inauguration did communicate with the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Bishops, and consequently were as then no<note n="(l)" place="margin">For <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> at his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secration out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly profes<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed himself, a Roman Catholic, taking the usual Oath of Fidelity to the Pope. <hi>Fox, Acts and Monuments p.</hi> 1690. See <hi>Champney, Vocation of Ministers, cap.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 369. <hi>Prudent. Ball.</hi> on <hi>Cranm. Examin of Fox his Acts and Monum.</hi>
               </note> professed Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, <hi>for with the Heart we believe unto Righteousness, and with the Mouth we profess unto Salvation,</hi> Rom. 10. v. 10.</p>
            <p n="40">40. If any Protestant allege, in behalf of their Succession, <hi>Waldo, Wickliff, Huss, &amp;c.</hi> I answer, first, they were all of them <hi>originally</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholics, and so prove only the precedent perpetuity of our Roman Church and no other more ancient, <hi>out of which</hi> (being then the only known Catholic Church) <hi>they departed</hi> and impugn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, a mark wherewith <hi>Christ</hi> and his Apostles usually branded<note n="(m)" place="margin">Go not forth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. <hi>v.</hi> 26. Certain which went out from us have troubled you, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.24. Many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers are gone out into the World, 2 <hi>John</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 7. They went out from us, but they were not of us, for if they had been of us they would no doubt have continued with us, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 19. Also of your own selves shall Men arise speaking perverse things, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 30. These be they who separate themselves, <hi>Jud. v.</hi> 19.</note> Heretics.</p>
            <p n="41">41. Secondly. They<note n="(n)" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Guido &amp; Anton. de Waldens. Illiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Catal. <hi>pag.</hi> 748, 749, 735. 756, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> taught many false and abominable Errors, <hi>Waldo</hi> &amp; his Followers taught, that <hi>Lay Men and Women might preach and consecrate, they denied all Judgments to Blood, they denied the Sabbath;</hi> and held, that <hi>Oaths were not lawful in any case: Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff</hi> and <hi>Huss</hi> maintained, that <hi>neither Bishop nor Priest being in mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Sin,</hi>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">Act. Mon. <hi>p.</hi> 96. Osiand. cent. 9, 10, 11. Protest. Apol. Tract. 2. cap. 2. Sect. 4. Subd. 2.</note>
               <hi>did ordain, consecrate, or baptize; Wickliff</hi> also taught, that <hi>there is no Civil Magistrate whilst he is in mortal Sin.</hi> Of their Errors more in particular, see the <hi>Protestant Apology, Tract.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. <hi>Subd.</hi> 2. and the <hi>Council of Constance, Sess.</hi> the 8th and 25th. where their Errors are related (in particular) and condemned: at which Council (procured by <hi>Sigismond</hi> the Emperor,) were present four Patriarchs, twenty nine Cardinals, Arch-Bishops forty seven, Bishops one hundred and sixty, Abbots and Doctors five hundred and sixty four, and betwixt <hi>Easter</hi> and <hi>Whitsunday</hi> were numbred in that City 60500 Externes or Strangers who came to that Council, <hi>Geneb. Harpsf. in Cron. in Hist. Eccles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="42">42. Lastly. None of these were <hi>Bishops,</hi> of whom only we enquire, for as before we<note n="(p)" place="margin">In the Text at Numb. 32. and Marginal Notes there: also at Number 31. and at Number 30.</note> proved at large without <hi>Bishops,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40980:12"/> there can be no Priest, without <hi>Priest</hi> no Ministry of the Word and Sacraments, without <hi>These</hi> no Church no Faith, no Salvation, which out of the true Catholic Church cannot be obtained.</p>
            <p n="43">43. For in this Point all the ancient Fathers unanimously and clearly consent. <hi>Whosoever will be saved, before all things, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary</hi> (saith blessed <hi>Athanasius) that he hold the Catholic Faith, which unless a Man keep</hi>
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">The reason is evident, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause one only false Doctrin maintained contumaciously against the Church, depriveth a Mans Soul of supernatural Faith, as one Act of Fornication depriveth him of Chastity, one Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Justice, one Murther of Charity; and consequently dissolveth that Union of Faith, whereby he was linked and incorporated into the Mystical Body of Christ, making him formally an <hi>Heretic,</hi> and Alien, from the Communion of Saints, 1 <hi>Cor. c.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>A little Leaven leaveneth,</hi> or corrupteth <hi>the whole Lump?</hi> For one word or two contrary to the Faith many Heresies have been cast out of the Church, St. <hi>Hierom, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Apol. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Ruffin.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>whole</hi> (or entire) <hi>and inviolable, without doubt, he shall perish everlastingly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="44">44. <q rend="margQuotes">Believe most firmly (saith
<note n="(r)" place="margin">St. <hi>Fulgent. de Fide ad Pet. cap.</hi> 3. Nothing can be more dangerous than those He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retics, who, when as they run through all things up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly; yet with one word, as with a drop of Poyson, corrupt and stain the true and sincere Faith of our Lord and of Apostolical Tradition, St. <hi>Greg. Nazian. de Fine,</hi> note the word, <hi>any,</hi> for <hi>Heresie</hi> damneth a man no less than <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Witchcraft.</hi> See expresly St. <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 19, 20, 21.</note> St. <hi>Fulgentius,</hi>) and in no wise doubt, but that every Heretic, and Schismatic, tho' baptized in the name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost, if he return not to the Catholic Church how great Alms soever he distribute, yea and tho' he shed his Blood for the Name of Christ, he can by no means be saved, for neither Baptism, nor most li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral Alms, nor death endured for the Name of Christ, can avail any man to Salvation, who holdeth not fast the Unity of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Church, or so long as any Heretical and Schismatical ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity remaineth in him.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="45">45. In like manner, St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> saith, <q rend="margQuotes">Whosoever and what kind of person soever a man be, a true Christian he is not, unless in the Church of Christ: And in
<note n="(s)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit. Prelat.</hi> and <hi>Epist.</hi> 62. <hi>ad Pomp. Theod. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Hist. cap.</hi> 17. reporteth of St. <hi>Basil the Great,</hi> that being by the Persecutors solicited to relent, he answered resolutely, that such as are instructed in Divine Doctrin, do not suffer any Syllable of the Divine Decrees to be depraved, but for Defence of it, if need require, willingly embrace any kind of Death.</note> another place; 'He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth not to the Reward of Christ, who forsaketh the Church of Christ, he is an Alien, a profane person, he is an Enemy he cannot have God for his Father, who hath not his Church for his Mother, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> If any man could escape out of the Ark of <hi>Noah,</hi> he also may escape who is out of the Church of God.</p>
            <p n="46">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:40980:13"/>46. <q rend="margQuotes">A man, saith St. <hi>August.</hi>
                  <note n="(t)" place="margin">De Unitate Ecclesiae lib. 4. c. 8. <hi>and</hi> tom. 7. Concione ad Plebem de E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merita post medium.</note> cannot obtain Salvation but in the Catholic Church; he may have all but Salvation; he may have the Sacraments, he may sing <hi>Alleluia,</hi> he may answer <hi>Amen,</hi> he may believe the Gospel, he may be baptized in the Name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost; but no where can he have Salvation but in the Catholic Church.</q> The like hath he, <hi>Epist.</hi> 50. <hi>ad Bonifacium Tom.</hi> 9. <hi>de Symbol. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p n="47">47. And yet more expresly, <q rend="margQuotes">Let us suppose (saith this Light of the Church,) that a man were chast and continent, not cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous but full of Hospitality, no enemy to any man, not conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious but patient,
<note place="margin">Lib. 4. contra Donatist. c. 8. <hi>See also</hi> Epist. 152.</note> and quiet, sober and frugal, not envying any, but withal were an Heretic, there can be no doubt <hi>made, but for that only, that he is an</hi> Heretic, <hi>he shall not possess the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> but the wrath of God remaineth on him.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="48">48. I conclude therefore with renowned
<note n="(u)" place="margin">Lib. 4. Divin. Instit. cap. ult. <hi>St.</hi> Hierom. de Script. Eccles. <hi>stileth him,</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteum Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentia flumen, <hi>he lived in the year of Christ</hi> 290. <hi>and was chosen to teach</hi> Crispus, <hi>Son to</hi> Constantine the Great.</note>
               <hi>Lactantius,</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">It is the Catholic Church only, that keepeth the true Worship of God; this is the Fountain of Truth, this is the House of Faith, this is the Temple of God, into which whosoever doth not enter, or out of which whoever doth depart, he is an Alien, and estranged from the hope of everlasting life and Salvation.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="49">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Aubert Miraeus <hi>his</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titia Episcopat. Baronius<hi>'s</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, <hi>Dr.</hi> Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders<hi>'s</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy; Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands Chron. Stapleton <hi>his</hi> Defence of Ecclesiastical Succession, Bellarm. de Rom. Pontif. <hi>Dr.</hi> Harpsf. Hist. Eccl. Angl. Prudential Ballance; Three Convers. Demochares de Instit. Miss. <hi>and to prevent all exception, Mr.</hi> Goodwin <hi>Protestant Bishop of</hi> Hereford <hi>in his</hi> Catalogue of the Bishops of <hi>England</hi> since the first planting of Christian Religion in this Island, which tho' begun in, and continued since the Apostles times, to the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th amongst the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Britains,</hi> yet hath he not there named any known and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged Protestant Bishop, before <hi>Thomas Cranmer</hi> in the Reign of the said King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, or noted any Change or Innovation of Religion to Protestancy, among so many Bishops before the time of <hi>Cranmer.</hi>
               </note>49 Now as touching the pereptual Succession both Personal and Doctrinal of our Bishops, because it is a matter often and exactly handled by our Divines and Ecclesiastical Histories, and would exceed my intended Brevity, I will forbear to set down their names and times of their Reign in the Church of God; he that desireth further Satisfaction, may peruse the Authors here cited in the Margent.</p>
            <p n="50">50. Briefly for the space of 400 years after Christ it is granted by learned<note n="(w)" place="margin">Whitt. lib. de Antichrist. cont Saunders, p. 35. Reynold. Confer. p. 41. <hi>and expresly,</hi> Calvin Instit. lib. 4 cap. 2. sect. 3. <hi>saith,</hi> It was a matter out of all doubt, that from the beginning even until that time, (<hi>viz.</hi> of St. <hi>Aug.</hi>) nothing was changed in Doctrin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> amongst the Roman Bishops.</note> Protestants, that there was no change of Faith in the Roman Bishops.</p>
            <p n="51">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:40980:13"/>51. Also St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> and St. <hi>Austin,</hi> (a Monk of St. <hi>Benedicts</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) planted here in <hi>England,</hi> our now Roman<note n="(x)" place="margin">
                  <hi>See this confessed not in general only, but in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted Doctrins by Dr.</hi> Humph. 2. Part of Jesuitism. pag. 627. Magdeburg. cent. 6. cap. 10. col. 448. Osiand cent. 6. pag. 29. Bale Catal. Scrip. Brit. cent. 14. pag 117.</note> Faith, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which neither King nor Bishop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> altered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, and <hi>Cranmer,</hi> as all Histories and Monuments of our Country bear witness.</p>
            <p n="52">52. Wherefore the Religion we now profess, can be no <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> or Change in us, nor the Roman Bishops, (with whom therein we communicate,) seeing we are certainly known and<note n="(y)" place="margin">See before immediately, Numb. 51. with Marginal Notes there, which you may find expressed at large in the Protestant Apology, Tract. 1. Sect. 1. <hi>and</hi> Tract. 1. Sect. 2. <hi>Mr.</hi> Nappier <hi>saith,</hi> The Pope and his Clergy possessed the outward visible Church 1200 years, <hi>Upon</hi> Revelat. cap. 11. pag. 161.</note>
               <hi>acknowledged</hi> to have continued in what we now profess, from this present to the time of St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> that is at the least a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand years.</p>
            <p n="53">53. Considering also, that four hundred and forty years after Christ, (that is unto the time of St. <hi>Augustin</hi> the Great,) the Roman Bishops retained inviolably the Doctrin received from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, as before was confessed by our Adversaries, if since that time we have revolted and made such Innovation in Faith, as Protestants do<note n="(z)" place="margin">
                  <hi>(Viz.)</hi> Touching the Law and Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, Faith and Works, Free Will and Grace, Prayers for the Dead, Prayer to Saints, Real Presence, Adoration of the Sacrament, Sacrifice of the Mass, Books of Scripture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> pretend, this great Alteration must necessarily fall out during the hundred and sixty years current between St. <hi>Augustin</hi> and St. <hi>Gregory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="54">54. Now God having placed<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Is.</hi> 62. <hi>v.</hi> 6. I have set Watch-men upon thy walls O <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> which shall never hold their peace, day nor night.</note> Watch-men in the Church, <hi>Bishops, Pastors</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> who neither day nor night shall cease, or be silent, but shall<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Fulk, Answer to a Counterfeit Catholic, pag. 11. 92.</note> resist all False Doctrin, even with open <hi>Reprehension;</hi> and seeing furthermore that this<note n="(c)" place="margin">In clear proof hereof, see the Ecclesiastical Histories and ancient Fathers, St. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius</hi> adversus Haereses, St. <hi>Augustin</hi> and <hi>Philast.</hi> their Catalogues of Heresies, <hi>Genebrand, Gualter, Pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olus, Arnoldus, Pontac.</hi> Chronology, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> resistance hath in all Ages been accordingly made, even to Errors and Heresies of less <hi>note: Heretical Impiety,</hi> saith St. <hi>Leo, could never so lie hid, but that it was by our Holy Fathers both observed and legally condemned.</hi> Serm. cont. Eutych.</p>
            <p n="55">55. These things (I say) supposed and duly considered if any
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40980:14"/> such <hi>Change</hi> or Alteration had been made by any of the Roman Bishops during these Hundred and sixty years (only Questionable,) then<note n="(d)" place="margin">For it was expresly so commanded by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim. c.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4, 5. and perpetually observed in the Church</note> assuredly some other Bishops, Pastors and Teachers would have<note n="(e)" place="margin">as they did in or immediately before the space questioned: The denial of Prayer and Sacrifice for the Dead in <hi>Aerius</hi> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured by St. <hi>Augustin</hi> Heres. 53. and <hi>Epiphanius</hi> Heres. 75. Honor of Relicts in <hi>Vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> censured by St <hi>Jerom</hi> cont. Vigilant. Equality of Merits in <hi>Jovinian,</hi> by St. <hi>Hier.</hi> cont. Jovin. Denial of the lawful use of Images in <hi>Zenaias.</hi> See <hi>Nicophor.</hi> Hist. Eccles. lib. 16. cap. 27. Denial of Free Will in the <hi>Manichees,</hi> condemned by St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> lib advers. <hi>Pelag.</hi> Denial of the Necessity of Childrens Baptism, in the <hi>Pelagians</hi> by <hi>Innocentius</hi> in the Rescript ad Concil. <hi>Milevit, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> noted them, some Council or Synod, Provincial, Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal or Oecumenical would have condemned them, and refused their Communion.</p>
            <p n="56">56. Whereas even during that mean space before mentioned, the Roman Bishops were not only not impeached or opposed for any such Change, or Innovation, but on the contrary the Bishops, both in the Eastern and Western Church, did communicate with them as with St. <hi>Leo</hi> the Great, the Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> and so with <hi>Hormisda, Hillary, Damasus, Innocentius, &amp;c.</hi> the most e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Churches of the Christian World, as is put beyond dispute by the Writers and Fathers of that Time. See <hi>Baroniu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> his Annals of those Hundred and sixty years questionable. Where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore doubtless no Change or Innovation was made <hi>then</hi> by the Roman Bishops, and so our Faith is concluded by perpetual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance one and the same with that of the precedent Ages, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially considering, that Mr. <hi>Nappier,</hi> upon the <hi>Revelations, cap.</hi> 11. <hi>pag.</hi> 161. acknowledgeth, that <hi>our Religion and Clergy reigned uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versally, even</hi> 1200 <hi>years, without any debateable contradiction,</hi> that is, sixty years within that compass of time beforementioned, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in learned Protestants acknowledge the Faith and Doctrin plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Apostles, to have remained in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Change. <hi>Sebast. Franc.</hi> before alledged, Numb. 37. alloweth 1400. years.</p>
            <p>Lastly. The Religion we now profess, is the same with tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which St. <hi>Augustin</hi> (a Monk of St. <hi>Benedicts</hi> Order) planted here in<note n="(f)" place="margin">See before Numb. 51. in the Margent.</note>
               <hi>England,</hi> and confirmed by<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>St.</hi> Gregory in Reg lib. 2. Epist. 30. Indic. 1. <hi>St</hi> Bede Hist. Angl. lib. 2. c. 2, <hi>and</hi> c. 3.</note> Miracles. Now<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Speed, l. 17. c. 18. p. 133. <hi>saith,</hi> On<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies they dissented, (viz. Austin <hi>and the</hi> Britains.) Fox, Acts and Mon. p. 463. <hi>saith,</hi> The Britains never forsook their Faith for any false Preaching or Torment. <hi>See also</hi> Fulk Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terf. Catho p. 44. Barlow, Defens. of Protest. Art. p. 21. Bale <hi>his</hi> Pageant of Popes.</note>
               <hi>Austin</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered not in substantial Points from the ancient <hi>Britains,</hi> (unless you will say the difference, in observing the Feast of <hi>Easter,</hi> was a substantial Point, where still the Protestants acknowledge the Error to have been on the <hi>Britains</hi> side:) neither had they at St. <hi>Austins</hi> coming <hi>(i)</hi> abandoned the Faith, which they had first
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40980:14"/> received from the Apostles and Disciples of Christ: ours there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in substantial Points, is the same with the Doctrin of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, Holy, Catholic, Apostolic.</p>
            <p>Wherefore be pleased to take into your consideration the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable and most dangerous estate wherein you now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main out of Communion with Gods Church, and in <hi>Corah</hi>'s con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Suffer not your self to be deluded with those fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Opinions, <hi>viz.</hi> that Errors not directly opposite to the Ground of Faith, cannot separate you from the true Church; or that Protestants differ not from Roman Catholics in funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Points of Religion.</p>
            <p>All Errors against Faith are <hi>damnable,</hi> if either your self do, or consent to those who do maintain them<note n="(i)" place="margin">They who in the Church of Christ, <hi>saith St.</hi> August. do maintain any unsound or wicked Doctrin, and admonished to believe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, do notwithstanding contumaciously resist, and will not amend their pestiferous and wicked Opinions, <hi>but</hi> persist to defend them, they are Heretics, <hi>St.</hi> August. de Civit. Dei, lib. 18. cap. 51. <hi>Alledged also to this purpose by St.</hi> Thomas, <hi>Prince of Divines,</hi> 1a. 2dae. Quest. 11. Art. 2. Sect. sed cont. <hi>Also Dr.</hi> Cowell <hi>a learned Protestant affirmeth,</hi> that they are Heretics, who gainsay some Articles of our Faith, Cowell Examin p. 199. And observe, that he requires not the Article to be fundamental; but some or any Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of our Faith.</note> obstinately against the true Church. See <hi>Aug. Enarr. in Psal.</hi> 130.</p>
            <p>For God is equally true in the<note n="(k)" place="margin">All Articles of Faith are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd by God, and who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately the least, doth not believe, that to be true which God revealeth, and so loseth his Faith, which is grounded on this, that whatsoever God revealeth, and by his Church propoundeth to our Belief, we ought undoubtedly to embrace; <hi>A little Leaven,</hi> saith the Apostle, <hi>leaveneth,</hi> or corrupteth, <hi>the whole Lump,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor. c.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 6. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 20. numbering Schisms and Sects of Heresies, amongst <hi>the Works of the Flesh,</hi> he concludeth, <hi>that they who do such things shall not inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception of great or small Heresie. Which Truth is yet further acknowledged by <hi>Luther</hi> himself, expresly affirming, that <hi>to deny God in one Article, is to deny him in all, for he is not divided into many, but he is all in every one, and one in all,</hi> Luther, Tom. 7. contra Sacram.</note>
               <hi>least</hi> and greatest Mysteries of our Faith which he revealeth, and by his Church<note n="(l)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Propoundeth by his Church, &amp;c.</hi> For God hath ordained his Church, as the means whereby he propoundeth dis Word, the proper Object of our Faith, and therefore tho' <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Jews</hi> believe one God, yet because they do not believe, that Truth for the Authority of God so propounding it by his Church, they have not therein true supernatural Faith. <hi>I,</hi> saith St. <hi>Augustin, would not believe the Gospel, if the Authority of the Catholic Church did not move me thereunto.</hi> August. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Epist. Fundam.</note> propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to our Belief, in the pertinacious denyal whereof, Heresie, as before we declared, doth properly consist.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:40980:15"/>
            <p>And therefore in the Apostolic and Primitive Times<note n="(m)" place="margin">For Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was condemned by the Apostles for holding, that Spiritual Gifts may be bought with Mony, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 20. The <hi>Nicholaites</hi> for Teaching, That it was lawful to eat of Meats sacrificed to Idols, and to commit Fornication, <hi>Revel. chap.</hi> 2. <hi>vers.</hi> 15. Also those whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> charged with the <hi>Doctrin of Devils,</hi> for prescribing to abstain from some Meats, as unclean, and from Marriage, as unlawful, 1 <hi>Tim. chap.</hi> 4. <hi>vers.</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. In like sort the <hi>Chiliasts,</hi> who Taught, that the Saints should reign on Earth with Christ a Thousand-Years after the Resurrection, <hi>Euseb.</hi> lib. 3. Hist. Eccles. cap. 39. the <hi>Quarto-decimans,</hi> who held, that <hi>Easter</hi>-day ought to be kept the Fourteenth day of the Moon, <hi>Aug.</hi> Heres. 19. with innumerable others, as the <hi>Helvidians, Jovinians, Vigilantians, Aquarians, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natists, &amp;c.</hi> And the Reason is evident, for as one Act of Fornication, with any who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever depriveth a Man of Chastity, one Act of Stealing depriveth him of Justice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So an Act of Herefic, against any Article of Faith, depriveth a Man of the supernatural Gift of Faith, as I said before.</note> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were condemned as <hi>Heretics,</hi> though their Errors were no <hi>directly</hi> opposite, to the Ground and Foundation of Religion that is, Belief in the Blessed Trinity, and Christ the Mediator.</p>
            <p>Now, that <hi>Protestants</hi> differ from us in <hi>Fundamental</hi> Points of Religion, is a matter so manifest, that I wonder any Man, knowing and believing the Common Grounds of Christianity, can rest doubtful thereof, for we differ almost contradictorily, in the<note n="(n)" place="margin">We hold Traditions of the Word of God unwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to belong to the Rule of Faith; they reject them: We believe as Canonical Scripture the Books of <hi>Wisdom, Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticus, Toby, Judith,</hi> two first of <hi>Maccabees,</hi> which Protestants deny; We hold se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Sacraments, they but two; We believe, that Christ in Spirit descended into Hell, which Article is denyed, and writ against by chief Protestants, See <hi>Willet</hi> his <hi>Limbo-Mastix.</hi> We believe by the Article <hi>Of the Catholic Church,</hi> that Church which is in Commuion of Faith, with the Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> but they hold the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church <hi>Anti-Christian;</hi> We believe the Remission of Sins, by the Sacrament of Baptism, and Penance; they by Faith alone; We hold the Commandments, by the help of Gods's Grace, may and have been kept; they hold they cannot. <hi>Calvin.</hi> lib. 2. Instit. cap. 7. Numb. 15. Antidot. Conc. Trident. Sess. 6. cap. 2.</note> Rule of Faith, Books of Scripture, Number and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Sacraments, Possibility of keeping the Commandments of God, and the external Sacrifice, and proper Priest-hood of the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover Protestants maintain sundry <hi>Heresies</hi>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">As Deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of Prayer and Sacrifice for the Dead, accounted as a Heresie in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> by St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustin,</hi> Haeres. 53. <hi>Epiphan.</hi> Haeres. 75. The Denyal of Prayer to Saints, and Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Relics, with <hi>Vigilantius,</hi> condemned by St. <hi>Hierom.</hi> contra Vigilant. The Denyal of Honor to Images, with <hi>Xenaias.</hi> See <hi>Nicephor.</hi> Hist. Eccles. lib. 16. cap. 27. Denyal of Free Will, condemned in the <hi>Manichees</hi> by St. <hi>Hierom. Praem.</hi> libr. contra Pelag. St. <hi>August.</hi> de Fide contra Manich. Denyal of the Necessity of Childrens Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptism, with the <hi>Pelagians;</hi> See <hi>Innocent</hi> Rescript. ad Concil. <hi>Milvitan.</hi> St. <hi>August.</hi> Haeres. 88. &amp; contra <hi>Jul. Pelag</hi> lib. 2. cap. 7. Denyal of Reservation of the Blessed Sacrament, with the <hi>Anthropomorphites.</hi> See St. <hi>Cyril</hi> ad Coelosyr. Confessed by <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Martyr,</hi> against <hi>Gardiner</hi> Object. 217. The Denyal of vowed Chastity, with <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinian; Hierom.</hi> contra <hi>Jovin.</hi> Denyal of perpetual Visibility of the Church, and the continuance thereof, with the <hi>Donatists; Aug.</hi> de Unitat. Eccles. cap. 12. Epist. 170, &amp;c.</note> condemned in the <hi>primitive</hi> Church and former Ages; wherefore by the Verdict of ancient Fathers<note n="(p)" place="margin">See Numb. 43, 44, 45, 46, 47, 48.</note> (before alledged to that purpose) remaining obstinately therein, they are out of Communion with the <hi>True Church</hi> of God, and consequently cannot arrive to Salvation, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they repent of those, and other their Errors.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:40980:15"/>
            <p>Hearken therefore to the Holy Ghost strictly commanding you under pain of Gods Wrath, to separate your self from He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical Assemblies, and all Participation of their Doctrin or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Worship, <hi>Come not ye unto</hi> Galgal, <hi>neither go up to</hi> Betha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, (places where Schismatical Sacrifices were offered) <hi>Hos.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>Come out of</hi> Babylon, <hi>my People, that ye be not Partakers of her Sin, and that ye receive not of her Plagues,</hi> Revel. 18.4. Also, Rom. 16. v. 17. <hi>I beseech you, my Brethren, mark them diligently, which cause Divisions (or Schism) and Offences</hi> (Scandals) <hi>contrary to the Doctrin which you have learned, and avoid them.</hi> 2 Thess. c. 3. v. 6. <hi>We command you, Brethren, in the Name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that you withdraw your selves from every Brother who walketh disorderly, and not after the Tradition</hi> (or Doctrin) <hi>which he receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of us.</hi> Also, 1 Tim. cap. 6. ver. 3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>If any man teach otherwise, and consent not to wholesom Words, even the Words of our Lord Jesus Christ, and to the Doctrin which is according to Godliness,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>From such withdraw thy self.</hi> In like manner, Tit. c. 3. v. 10. <hi>A Man that is an Heretic, after the first and second Admonition, reject:</hi> Devita, avoid, <hi>knowing, that he that is such, is subverted, and sinneth, being condemned of himself:</hi> Proprio Judicio, by his own Judgment. But most expresly, 2 Cor. cap. 6. v. 14, <hi>&amp;c. What Fellowship hath Righteousness with Ʋnrighteousness? What Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath Light with Darkness? And what Concord hath Christ with</hi> Belial? <hi>Or what part hath he that believeth with the Infidel? And what agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols? For ye are the Temple of the Living God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Wherefore, come out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and separate your selves, saith the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and I will receive you.</hi> Thus far that blessed Apostle, who though he spake immediately of Heathenish Idolatry, yet his Words are to be understood also of <hi>Schism</hi> and <hi>Heresie,</hi> which all Men confess to be <hi>Spiritual Idolatry,</hi> worshiping that for Divine, which in it self is false, and the <hi>Idol</hi> of their own Imaginations, so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly doth St. <hi>Hierom</hi> affirm upon <hi>Ezekiel</hi> c. 8. <hi>Hos.</hi> c. 11. <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi> 13. <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. And St. <hi>Aug.</hi> upon <hi>Josua</hi> c. 27.</p>
            <p>Ponder, I beseech you, with mature deliberation,<note place="margin">Numb. 16.</note> that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Judgment of God against <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram.</hi> who
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40980:16"/> worshiped the same God with <hi>Moses,</hi> and dissented not from him in fundamental Points of Faith and Religion, but only by <hi>Schism</hi> and Usurpation rose up against him and <hi>Aaron,</hi> taking upon them without Lawful Calling the Office of Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, as from what has been said you cannot but have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to fear, if not perfectly convinced, the Ministers do with whom you<note n="(q)" place="margin">That Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Lawful Calling; See at large <hi>Champhrey</hi> his Book of Vocation of Ministers; <hi>Prud. Ball.</hi> lib. 2. cap. 10. <hi>Harding</hi> his Detection of <hi>Jewel,</hi> Title of Succession; See also before from Numb. 30, to 40. For if they claim <hi>Extraordinary</hi> Vocation: Let them shew us their Miracles in proof thereof; if <hi>Ordinary,</hi> let them name so much as one Protestant Bishop before <hi>Cranmer,</hi> from whom they can derive it: And our Bishops neither did, nor could give them Authority to Minister the <hi>Protestant Word and Sacaments,</hi> for they never did receive any such Power from their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors.</note> communicate.</p>
            <p>And yet God expresly saith to his People, Numbers 16. v. 21. v. 3. <hi>Separate your selves from amidst the Congregation, that I may consume them in a moment.</hi> And v. 24. <hi>Get ye up from about the Tabernacle of</hi> Corah, Dathan <hi>and</hi> Abiram. Also, v. 26. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the Tents of these wicked Men, lest ye be consumed in all their Sins.</hi> And that none might conceive the Offence of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Schismatics and Heretics to be small, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardable, he poured out his Indignation upon them, for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and dreadful warning to all in like case; for as the Text saith, <hi>v.</hi> 31. <hi>The ground clave asunder, that was under them, and the Earth opened her Mouth and swallowed them up, and their Families, and all their Men that were with them, and all their Goods.</hi> And vers. 35. <hi>There came out a Fire from the Lord, and consumed the Two Hundred and Fifty Men that offered Incense.</hi> Yea the morrow fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, when the People murmured against <hi>Moses</hi> for the severe Punishment of these <hi>Schismatics,</hi> the Wrath and Plague of God light amongst them, and there died Fourteen Thousand and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Hundred, besides them that perished with <hi>Corah, vers.</hi> 49. Furthermore, that none might think this Punishment to have been in regard of these Schismatics alone, read in the same place, <hi>vers.</hi> 38, 39, and 40. where God ordained a perpetual Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance thereof to remain at the Altar, as a dreadful Memorial from Generation to Generation, to the end that others warned thereby may beware of Schism, and participation with Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matics, much more of Communion with Heritics.</p>
            <p>Give me leave therefore once again to entreat, nay to impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune you by the tender Mercies of God, and that precious Blood, the Price of our Redemption, no longer to delay, but hasten out
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40980:16"/> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and return speedily to the Bosom of Gods Church. Let the Scandalous Lives of some few (whether in former or in these present times) banish you from Communion with the true Catholic Church, out of which your Soul cannot be safe: rather take into consideration, that in Heaven also there was a Lucifer, with millions of Angels his Complices; in Paradise but one Precept for two, and both Transgressors; in the Ark of <hi>Noah</hi> Creatures clean and unclean; with <hi>Abel</hi> a <hi>Cain,</hi> a <hi>Cham</hi> with <hi>Sem;</hi> with <hi>Jacob</hi> an <hi>Esau;</hi> and amongst Twelve elected by Christ, <hi>one</hi> (as Truth it self affirmed)<note n="(r)" place="margin">1 Joh. 6 7.</note>
               <hi>was a Devil.</hi> In which respect in the Gospel, Christs Church is compared to<note n="(s)" place="margin">Matth. 13.14. Luke 5.3.</note>
               <hi>a Field,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Corn with Tares, to a <hi>Net</hi> comprehending good and evil Fish; a <hi>House</hi> in which as there are Vessels of Gold and Silver; so are there others of Wood and Earth; with Five wise Virgins, as many foolish; and at the Marriage Feast some without their Nuptial Garments of Charity; and our Saviour himself, to take off the Calumny from his Church, for defects in some of his Pastors, expresly denounceth their Authority, and exacteth obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience thereunto, though their Living be not conformable to their Doctrin, Matth. 23. vers. 1. <hi>Ʋpon the Chair of</hi> Moses <hi>sit the Scribes and Pharisees; therefore whatsoever they bid you observe, that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve and do, but do not after their works, for they say, and do not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">St. <hi>Aug.</hi> Epist. 165.</note> In that Order of Bishops (saith St. <hi>Aug.</hi> of the Roman See) albeit some <hi>Judas,</hi> albeit some Traytor should enter, yet should it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing prejudice the Church, and innocent Christians, for whom our Lord providing said, what they prescribe you do, but do not according their works.</p>
            <p>Hasten therefore, Worthy Sir, and hearken to the Wisdom of God, advising you to cut off delays<note n="(t)" place="margin">Joh. 12.45.</note> and run whilst the Light of Life serveth, lest the Darkness of Night overtake you,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Joh. 9.</note>
               <hi>for Night will come, when no Man can work.</hi> There is always danger in delay, and in business of this Nature, the greatest; for Custom of Sin thereby will grow strong, our Forces weak; old Diseases are hardly cured, new Impediments daily increase, Life decreaseth and Death approacheth with a dreadful accompt and Gods Indignation.</p>
            <p>Entertain therefore, Dear Sir, while you have time and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, that wholesome Counsel of the Holy Ghost admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing <hi>not to</hi>
               <note n="(w)" place="margin">Eccles. 5.8.</note>
               <hi>delay your Conversion to God, nor to defer it from day to day, for his Wrath will come upon a sudden, and in time of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge he will destroy you.</hi> And lest you should imagin, this time further off, he proclaimeth to us<note n="(x)" place="margin">Deut. 32.</note> all; the day of Destruction is near at hand, and times make hast to be present; wherefore mercifully and lovingly he inviteth<note n="(y)" place="margin">Apoc. 3.</note> us <hi>to seek God while he may be found, and call upon him while he is near,</hi> otherwise he that now
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40980:17"/>
               <hi>standeth at the door</hi>
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">Prov. 1.24, 25, 26.</note> of our Heart, <hi>knocking</hi> with so many godly Inspirations, will at length through our obduration be forced to say, (as he doth by <hi>Solomon) I called, and ye refused; I stretched out my hands, and there was none that regarded; you have despised all my Counsels, and have neglected my Reprehensions: I will laugh in your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, and will scorn when that shall come upon you which you feared, when sudden Calamities shall rush upon you, and Destruction as a Tempest shall be at hand, then shall they invocate me, and I will not hear, in the morning they shall rise, and shall not find me; for they have hated Discipline, and have not received the Fear of the Lord: therefore shall they eat the fruit of their own way, and be filled with their own devices: the aversion of little ones shall kill them, and the prosperity of Fools shall destroy them: but he that feareth me shall rest without terror, and enjoy abundance without fear of Evil.</hi> Hear him therefore now and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve his Commandments, that you may possess him in time and Eternity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:40980:17"/>
            <head>Copies of two Papers written by the late King <hi>Charles II.</hi> of Blessed Memory.</head>
            <div type="paper">
               <head>The first Paper.</head>
               <p>THE Discourse we had the other Day, I hope satisfied you in the main, <hi>That Christ can have but one Church here upon Earth;</hi> and I believe that it is as visible, as that the Scripture is in Print, That none can be that Church, but that which is called the <hi>Roman Catholic Church.</hi> I think you need not trouble your self with the entring into that Ocean of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Disputes, when the main, and in truth, the only Question is, Where that Church is, which we profess to believe in the two Creeds? We declare there to believe one Catholic and Apostolic Church, and it is not left to every Phantastical Man's head to believe as he pleases, but to the Church, to whom Christ left the Power upon Earth to govern us in matters of Faith, who made these Creeds for our Directions. It were a very irrational thing to make Laws for a Country, and leave it to the Inhabitants to be the Interpreters and Judges of those Laws: For then every Man will be his own Judge, and by consequence no such thing as either Right or Wrong. Can we therefore suppose that God Almighty would leave us at those Uncertainties, as to give us a Rule to go by, and leave every Man to be his own Judge? I do ask any ingenuous Man, whether it be not the same thing to follow our own P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ancy, or to Interpret the Scripture by it? I would have any Man shew me, where the Power of deciding matters of Faith is given to every particular Man. Christ left his Power to his Church <hi>even to forgive Sins in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and left his Spirit with them, which they exercised after his Resurrection: First by his Apostles in their Creeds, and many
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40980:18"/> Years after by the Council at <hi>Nice,</hi> where that Creed was made that is called by that Name: And by the Power which they had received from Christ, they were the Judges even of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it self, many years after the Apostles, which Books were Canonical and which were not. And if they had this Power then, I desire to know how they came to lose it, and by what Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority Men separate themselves from that Church? The only Pretence I ever heard of, was, because the Church has failed in wrestling and interpreting the Scripture contrary to the true Sense and meaning of it, and that they have imposed Articles of Faith upon us, which are not to be warranted by God's Word. I do desire to know who is to be Judge of that, whether the whole Church, the Succession whereof has continued to this Day without interruption; or particular Men, who have raised Schisms for their own Advantage?</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>This is a true Copy of a Paper I found in the late King my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> Strong Box, <hi>written in his own Hand.</hi> J. R.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="paper">
               <head>The Second Paper.</head>
               <p>IT is a sad thing to consider, what a World of <hi>Heresies</hi> are crept into this Nation; every Man thinks himself as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent a Judge of the Scriptures, as the very Apostles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; and 'tis no wonder that it should be so, since that part of the Nation which looks most like a Church, dares not bring the true Arguments against the other Sects, for fear they should be turn'd against themselves, and confuted by their own Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The Church of <hi>England</hi> (as it is call'd) would fain have it thought, They are the Judges in matters Spiritual, and yet dare not say positively there is no Appeal from Them: For ei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther they must say, that They are Infallible (which they canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pretend to) or confess, That what they decide in matters of Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>science, is no farther to be followed than it agrees with every
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40980:18"/> Man's private Judgment. If Christ did leave a Church here up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, and we were all once of that Church; How and by what Authority, did we separate from that Church? If the Power of Interpreting of Scripture be in every Man's Brain, what need have We of a Church or Church men? To what purpose then did our Saviour, after he had given his Apostles power to bind and loose in Heaven and Earth, add to it, <hi>That he would be with Them even to the End of the World?</hi> These Words were not spoken Parabolically or by way of Figure: Christ was then A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scending into his Glory, and <hi>left his Power with his Church even to the End of the World.</hi> We have had these Hundred years past, the sad effects of denying to the Church that Power in matters Spiritual, without an Appeal. What Country can sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist in peace or quiet, where there is not a Supreme Judge, from whence there can be no Appeal? Can there be any Justice done where the Offenders are their own Judges, and equal Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Law, with those, who are appointed to administer Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice? This is our case here in <hi>England</hi> in matters Spiritual: For the <hi>Protestants</hi> are not of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as 'tis the true Church from whence there can be no Appeal, but because the Discipline of that Church is conformable at that present to their Phancies, which as soon as it shall contradict or vary from, They are ready to embrace or join with the next Congregation of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whose Discipline or Worship agrees with their own Opinion at that time; so that according to this Doctrin, there is no other Church, nor Interpreter of Scripture, but that which lies in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Mans giddy Brain. I desire to know therefore of every serious Considerer of these things, whether the great Work of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation ought to depend upon such a sandy Foundation as this? Did Christ ever say to the Civil Magistrates (much less to the People) <hi>That He would be with Them to the End of the World?</hi> Or did he give Them the Power to forgive Sins? St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Corinthians, Ye are Gods Husbandry, Ye are Gods Building, We are Laborers with God,</hi> This shews who are the Laborers, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40980:19"/> who are the Husbandry, and Building? And in this whole Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and in the preceding one, St. <hi>Paul</hi> takes great pains to set forth, that They, <hi>(the Clergy) have the Spirit of God, without which no Man searches the deep things of God.</hi> And he concludes the Chapter with this Verse, <hi>For who hath known the mind of the Lord, that he might instruct him? But we have the mind of Christ.</hi> Now if we but consider in human Probability and Reason, the Powers Christ leaves to his Church in the Gospel, and St. <hi>Pau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> explains so distinctly afterwards; we cannot think that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>viour said all these things to no purpose: And pray consider on the other side, that those who Resist the Truth, and will not sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to his Church, draw their Arguments from Implications, and far fetch'd Interpretations, at the same time that they deny plai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and positive Words; which is so great a Dis-ingenuity, as 'tis not almost to be thought, that they can believe themselves. Is there any other Foundation of the <hi>Protestant Church,</hi> but that, if the Civil Magistrate please, He may call such of the Clergy as he thinks fit for his turn at that time, and turn the Church either to <hi>Presbytery, Independency,</hi> or indeed what he pleases? This was the Way of our pretended Reformation here in <hi>England.</hi> And by the same Rule and Authority it may be alter'd into as many more Shapes and Forms as there are Fancies in Mens Heads.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>This is a true Copy.</hi> J. R.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="recollection">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:40980:19"/>
            <head>A Brief Account of particulars occurring at the happy Death of our late Sovereign Lord King <hi>CHARLES II.</hi> in regard to Religion; faithfully related by his then Assistant, Mr <hi>John Hudleston.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>UPon <hi>Thursday</hi> the Fifth of <hi>February,</hi> 1685. Between Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Eight a Clock in the Evening, I was sent for in hast to the Queens Back stairs at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired to bring with me all things necessary for a dying Person. Accordingly I came, and was order'd not to stir from thence till further notice; being thus obliged to wait, and not having had time to bring along with me the Most Holy Sacrament of the Altar, I was in some Anxiety how to procure it: In this conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture (the Divine Providence so disposing) Father <hi>Bento de Lemos</hi> a <hi>Portugez</hi> came thither, and understanding the circumstance I was in, readily profer'd himself to go to St. <hi>James</hi>'s and bring the Most Holy Sacrament along with him.</p>
            <p>Soon after his departure I was call'd into the Kings Bed Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where approaching to the Bed side, and Kneeling down, I in brief presented his Majesty with what service I could perform for God's honor, and the happiness of his Soul at this last Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on which Eternity depends. The King then declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, That he desired to die in the Faith and Communion of the Holy Roman Catholic Church, That he was most heartily sorry for all the Sins of his life past, and particularly for that he had deferred his Reconciliation so long; That through the Merits of Christ's Passion he hoped for Salvation, That he was in Charity with all the World; that with all his heart he Pardon'd his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and desired Pardon of all those whom he had any wise of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, and that if it pleased God to spare him longer Life, he would amend it, detesting all Sin.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:40980:20"/>
            <p>I then advertis'd His Majesty of the benefit and necessity of the Sacrament of Penance, which advertisement the King most willingly embracing, made an exact Confession of his whole Life with exceeding Compunction and Tenderness of Heart, which ended, I desired him, in farther sign of Repentance and true sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for his Sins, to say with me this little short Act of Contrition.</p>
            <p>O my Lord God, with my whole Heart and Soul I detest all the Sins of my Life past for the Love of Thee, whom I love a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, and I firmly purpose by thy Holy Grace never to offend thee no more, <hi>Amen</hi> Sweet Jesus. <hi>Amen.</hi> Into thy hands sweet Jesus I commend my Soul, Mercy, sweet Jesus, Mercy. This he pronounced with a clear and audible voice, which done, and his Sacramental Penance admitted, I gave him Absolution.</p>
            <p>After some time thus spent, I asked His Majesty, if he did not also desire to have the other Sacraments of the Holy Church ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministred to him? He replyed, by all means, I desire to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of all the helps and succours necessary and expedient for a Catholic Christian in my condition. I added, and doth not your Majesty also desire to Receive the Pretious Body and Blood of our dear Saviour Jesus Christ in the Most Holy Sacrament of the Eucharist? His Answer was this: If I am worthy, pray fail not to let me have it. I then told him, it would be brought to him very speedily and desired his Majesty, that in the interim he would give me leave to proceed to the Sacrament of Extreme Unction, he replyed with all my Heart; I then anointed him, which as soon as perform'd I was called to the Door, whither the blessed Sacrament was now brought and delivered to me.</p>
            <p>Then returning to the King, I entreated His Majesty, that he would prepare and dispose himself to receive. At which the King raising up himself, said, let me meet my Heavenly Lord in a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter posture than in my Bed. But I humbly begg'd His Majesty to repose himself: God Almighty who saw his Heart would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of his good intention. The King then having again reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40980:20"/> the forementioned Act of Contrition with me, he received the Most Holy Sacrament for his Viaticum with all the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms of Devotion imaginable. The Communion being ended I Read the usual Prayers, termed the Recommendation of the Soul, appointed by the Church for Catholics in his condition. After which the King desired the Act of Contrition: O my Lord God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be repeated, this done, for his last Spiritual encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement I said.</p>
            <p>Your Majesty hath now received the Comfort and Benefit of all the Sacraments, that a good Christian (ready to depart out of this World) can have or desire. Now it rests only, That you think upon the Death and Passion of our Dear Saviour Jesus Christ of which I present unto you this Figure (shewing him a Crucifix) lift up therefore the Eyes of your Soul and represent to your self your sweet Saviour here Crucified: Bowing down his Head to Kiss you: His Arms stretched out to Embrace you: His Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Members all Bloody and Pale with Death to Redeem you: And as you see him Dead and fixed upon the Cross for your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; So have his Remembrance fixed and fresh in your Heart: beseech him with all Humility, that his most precious Blood may not be shed in vain for you: And that it will please him by the Merits of his bitter Death and Passion to pardon and forgive you all your Offences, and finally to receive your Soul into his blessed Hands, and when it shall please him to take it out of this Transitory World, to grant you a joyful Resurrection and an Eternal Crown of Glory in the next. In the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So Recommending His Majesty on my Knees, with all the Transport of Devotion I was able, to the Divine Mercy and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection I withdrew out of the Chamber.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>In Testimony of all which I have hereunto subscribed my Name. JO. HƲDLESTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:40980:21"/>
            <head>Books printed and sold by <hi>Will. Weston,</hi> Printer and Stationer to His Excellency the Lord Deputy.</head>
            <list>
               <item>ABridgment of Christian Doctrine with Proofs of Scripture.</item>
               <item>The little Vade Mecum, or continual Companion of a Devout Christian.</item>
               <item>Belarmin's Christian Doctrine.</item>
               <item>Ledezma's Christian Doctrine.</item>
               <item>Jesus Psalter.</item>
               <item>Rosary of our B. Lady.</item>
               <item>St. Bridgets Prayers.</item>
               <item>The Mysteries of the Holy Mass.</item>
               <item>Holy Sacrifice of the Mass in English expounded.</item>
               <item>The Fryer Disciplined.</item>
               <item>Small Manuals.</item>
               <item>Christian Thoughts for every day in the Month.</item>
               <item>Nets for the Fishers of Men.</item>
               <item>The Maxims of Eternity.</item>
               <item>Prayers for the King in Latine and English.</item>
               <item>The Impostor, posted, or the Author of the Protestant Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution proved no Protestant of the Church of England.</item>
               <item>New Forms of Meditations.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:40980:21"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>